<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mans mortalitie: or, A treatise wherein 'tis proved, both theologically and philosophically, that whole man (as a rationall creature) is a compound wholly mortall, contrary to that common distinction of soule and body: and that the present going of the soule into heaven or hell is a meer fiction: and that at the resurrection is the beginning of our immortality, and then actual condemnation, and salvation, and not before. : With all doubts and objections answered, and resolved, both by scripture and reason; discovering the multitude of blasphemies, and absurdities that arise from the fancie of the soule. : Also divers other mysteries, as, of heaven, hell, Christs humane residence, the extent of the resurrection, the new creation, &amp;c. opened, and presented to the tryall of better judgments. / By R.O.</title>
            <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O629E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097881</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2575:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mans mortalitie: or, A treatise wherein 'tis proved, both theologically and philosophically, that whole man (as a rationall creature) is a compound wholly mortall, contrary to that common distinction of soule and body: and that the present going of the soule into heaven or hell is a meer fiction: and that at the resurrection is the beginning of our immortality, and then actual condemnation, and salvation, and not before. : With all doubts and objections answered, and resolved, both by scripture and reason; discovering the multitude of blasphemies, and absurdities that arise from the fancie of the soule. : Also divers other mysteries, as, of heaven, hell, Christs humane residence, the extent of the resurrection, the new creation, &amp;c. opened, and presented to the tryall of better judgments. / By R.O.</title>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
                  <author>Writer, Clement, fl. 1627-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Canne.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno dom. 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Richard Overton, aided by Clement Writer"--Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Future life.</term>
               <term>Immortality.</term>
               <term>Soul.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> MANS MORTALITIE: OR, A TREATISE Wherein 'tis proved, both Theologically and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically, that whole Man (as a <hi>rationall Creature</hi>) is a Compound wholly mortall, contrary to that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſtinction of <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Body:</hi> And that the preſent going of the <hi>Soule</hi> into <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi> is a meer <hi>Fiction:</hi> And that at the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is the beginning of our <hi>immortality,</hi> and then Actuall <hi>Condemnation,</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> and not before.</p>
            <p>With all doubts and Objections Anſwered, and reſolved, both by Scripture and Reaſon; diſcovering the multitude of <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> and Abſurdities that ariſe from the fancie of the <hi>Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo divers other Myſteries, as, of Heaven, Hell, Chriſts humane reſidence, the extent of the Reſurrection, the New Creation, &amp;c. opened, and preſented to the tryall of better judgments.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. O.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>That which befalleth the ſons of men, befalleth beaſts; even one thing befalleth them all: as the one dyeth, ſo dyeth the other; yea they have all one breath, ſo that man hath no preheminence above a beaſt; for all is vanity.</hi> 
               <bibl>Eccleſiaſtes 3. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>AMSTERDAM, Printed by <hi>John Canne. Anno Dom.</hi> 1644.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171460:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171460:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Judicious Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THy ſerious peruſall, but the ſcorne and deriſion of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude hereof, is my expectation: Startle not thou, be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, read, ponder, and <hi>Berean</hi> like try whether theſe things be ſo or no: If any thing in it be worth thy owning, take it, it is thine as well as mine, and I have my end, <hi>thy benefit:</hi> I wiſh it well to all, but I feare it will be a <hi>Parable</hi> to moſt; however, I have unboſom'd my duty, freely as I have received, I give it freely to the World; it is my faith, as I beleeve, ſo have I ſpoken. I expect an <hi>Anſwer;</hi> if it be ſuch as will not hold tryall, it is likely I ſhall vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate my ſelfe; but if by force of Argument it ſhall convince, I ſhall be ready and free thankfully to embrace it, and renounce my errour, whether it be in part or in whole, though in the maine I am nothing jealous, had I therein doubted, my weakneſſe had not been thus viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the World. Whereas in ſeverall places ſcattered through the <hi>Booke,</hi> the uſe of the word <hi>Soule</hi> may ſeeme to ſome, to imply that, which I deny; let ſuch know, it is for Argument ſake, not intending in the leaſt any ſelfe diſtinct Being by it. Thus deſiring my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours may have a faire and equall tryall by <hi>Scripture</hi> and ſollid <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I commit thee to the bleſsing of God in the peruſall thereof, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the love of the Truth, <hi>R. O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:171460:3"/>
            <head>To his worthy friend the Author upon his Booke.</head>
            <l>THe Hell hatch'd Doctrine of th'immortall Soule</l>
            <l>Diſcovered, makes the hungry <hi>Furies</hi> houle,</l>
            <l>And teare their ſnakey haire with griefe appal'd,</l>
            <l>To ſee their Errour-leading Doctrine quail'd,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hell</hi> undermin'd, and <hi>Purgatory</hi> blowne</l>
            <l>Vp in the <hi>aire,</hi> and all the <hi>ſpirits</hi> flowne,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pluto</hi> undone, thus forced for to yeeld</l>
            <l>The frightned <hi>Soules</hi> from the <hi>Elizian Field.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ſquallid <hi>Charon</hi> now may leave his <hi>Trade,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To ſee <hi>all Soules</hi> made ſubject to the <hi>ſpade,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>Cerberus</hi> his diſmall fate deplore,</l>
            <l>To thinke that he ſhall <hi>ſcare</hi> the <hi>Soules no more.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But joy'd at this, <hi>Minerva</hi> ſhe doth run</l>
            <l>T'imbrace her Nurſe Child <hi>great Apollo's</hi> Son:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Heavens</hi> triumph i'th' wane of th'World to ſee</l>
            <l>Such <hi>light</hi> break out on its Poſteritie:</l>
            <l>They ſue <hi>Mneſichole,</hi> and ſo doe I</l>
            <l>To <hi>regiſter</hi> this <hi>Mans Mortalitie.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <l>VVOuld you a <hi>young Man</hi> ſee for to <hi>controule</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Antient</hi> ſure you'd think he had no <hi>ſoul.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But God hath promiſed, and ſtill reveales</l>
            <l>To <hi>Babes,</hi> what he from <hi>prudent</hi> men conceales.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Heavens</hi> bleſſe thee <hi>Man,</hi> for bringing that to light,</l>
            <l>Which Envy raked up i'th' duſt for ſpight:</l>
            <l>And may thy <hi>Booke</hi> be as a <hi>paſſing Bell</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To dying Man to <hi>toll</hi> his fatall <hi>knell.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171460:3"/>
            <head>MANS MORTALITY. OR, <hi>A Treatiſe proving MAN</hi> (quatenus Animal rationale) <hi>a Compound wholly Mortall.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Mans Creation, Fall, Reſtitution, and Reſurrection, how they diſprove the Opinion of the Soul, imagining the better part of Man immortall: And proveth him</hi> (quatenus homo) <hi>wholly mortall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO omit tedious introductory Circumſtances, which are as commonly vſeleſſe as prolix: Obſerve: That when God had moulded, formed, and compleatly proportionated <hi>Adam of the Duſt of the ground, he breathed in his face the breath of Lives</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Orig.</note>, <hi>and Man became a living Soul: Gen.</hi> 2. 7. That is, he gave that life-leſſe Body a communicative rationall Faculty or property of life, in his kind: And ſo it became a living Creature, or compleate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of whom was the <hi>Woman,</hi> both innocent and free from ſin, and ſo from <hi>Death</hi> and mortality: For <hi>the wages of Sin is Death, Rom.</hi> 5. 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 56. Thus Man was gloriouſly immortall, yet no longer a Creature incorruptible, then during innocent: For <hi>(Gen.</hi> 2. 17.) God ſaid, <hi>of the Tree of the knowledge of good and evill thou ſhalt not eate of it, for in the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> that is, thy immortality ſhall be changed for mortality: Immortall <hi>Adam</hi> ſhall be made mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, not a part of thee, but <hi>Thou</hi> ſhalt ſurely dye, even whole man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt exception of any, the worſt or nobleſt part of him, unleſſe God had a mentall reſervation; but even the ſame <hi>Thou</hi> that liveſt, <hi>Thou</hi> ſhalt ſurely dye: <hi>that muſt dye wherein was life:</hi> then ſurely if he had an immortall Soul, which is the life of the body, that muſt be made mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. The reſult of all which, is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That what of</hi> Adam <hi>was immortall through Innocency, was to be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talized by Tranſgreſſion:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But whole</hi> Adam (quatenus Animal rationale) <hi>was in Innocency im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall:</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171460:4"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Ergo, all, and every part, even whole Man was lyable to Death by Sin:</hi> And ſo conſequently, if <hi>Adam</hi> had <hi>then</hi> ſuch an indefinable thing in him, and of him, without which he was not Man, (as is vulgarly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but ſimply maintained by the Church of <hi>Rome, England</hi> &amp;c.) as an Angelical <hi>Spirit,</hi> that neither could, nor can be ſubject to mortality: Then he had that he had not: which made him be what he was not: he <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Abſur.</hi>
                  </note> ſinned with that, with which he could not; which made him Fall <note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Abſur.</hi>
                  </note> when he did not: which <hi>Bo-peepe</hi> is impoſſible: For if <hi>Adam</hi> was martalized, and <hi>That</hi> not, <hi>It</hi> was no part of him, this they muſt confeſſe, or elſe the other followes.</p>
               <p>This being thus cleared, and proved from <hi>Adams Creation</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency:</hi> let us proceed to his <hi>Fall, Reſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> who eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>forbidden fruit,</hi> (whoſe nature was, as was ſuppoſed by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſius</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> to mortalize him, as <hi>Mala inſana</hi> are to deſtroy and reduce rationality to madneſſe) God fulfilled his threatned <hi>Curſe</hi> upon him, ſaying, <hi>(Gen.</hi> 3. 19.) <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eate bread, till thou returne unto the Ground; for out of it waſt thou taken: for Duſt thou art, and unto Duſt thou ſhalt returne.</hi> Here he is plainly diſrobed of all his immortality, he muſt to <hi>Duſt,</hi> without the leaſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any <hi>Being</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Man had died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad not Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed it: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>herefore, aſwel may we ſay, that all ſhall not riſe, as that Chriſt died not for all; for if one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be, needs muſt the other.</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 21. 22.</note> thereafter, either of part or whole; till this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall breake the Serpents Head,</hi> which is not compleated till the <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> for then, and not before, Mans immortality is in <hi>Actuall Being,</hi> whoſe beatitude and infelicity comes through Faith and infidelity. So that Death reduceth this <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductio Entis ex Non-ente ad Non-entem,</hi> returnes Man to what he was before he was; that is, <hi>not to Be: Pſal.</hi> 115. 47. <hi>the Dead prayſe not the Lord, neither they that go down into ſilence:</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 4. <hi>His breath goeth forth, he returneth to the Earth, in that</hi> very Day <hi>his thoughts pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> (ſee more <hi>pag.</hi> 5. 6. 7. 8.) But the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> reſtoreth this non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ented Entitie to an everlaſting <hi>Being,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 42. <hi>It is ſowne in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, it is raiſed in incorruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Mortality</hi> is derivated to all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity: <hi>The firſt Man</hi> (quatenus homo) <hi>is of the Earth earthly, as is the earthly, ſuch are they that are earth:</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 47. 48.) But the Earth of which Man <hi>is,</hi> is corruptible, and ſhallbe <hi>burnt up</hi> with fire: 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 10. Therefore whole Man is corruptible: for <hi>as in Adam all dye,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 22) <hi>even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive;</hi> what fell in <hi>Adam</hi> ſhall be raiſed by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> what was mortalized by the <hi>earthly Man</hi> ſhall be immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized by the <hi>Heavenly man:</hi> wherefore <hi>All,</hi> not a part of Man was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talized by <hi>Adam;</hi> or elſe onely the fallen <note n="c" place="margin">3. <hi>Abſur.</hi>
                  </note> part muſt be redeemed, and
<pb facs="tcp:171460:4"/> not the whole man: for no more of man then fell was redeemed, and if the body only fell, and his formall part (his ſoul) continued immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, then that part of man (his body only) was purchaſed, not his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutive or better part, his Soul: So that the bodies <note n="d" place="margin">4. <hi>Abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> only of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate according to this fancy ſhall be damned: for nothing of <hi>Adam,</hi> but what fell of <hi>Adam,</hi> can be made lyable to condemnation; and what of him ſtood, ſhall ſtand, as well as the <hi>Angels</hi> that never fell: But <hi>in Chriſt we are compleate, Coll.</hi> 2. 10. Therefore in <hi>Adam</hi> totally fallen.</p>
               <p>Further: If <hi>Adams fall</hi> was not a compleat change of his whole man-hood, from immortality to abſolute mortality of the whole; then <note n="e" place="margin">5. <hi>Abſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in the day that he did eate</hi> (the forbidden Fruit,) <hi>He did not ſurely dye;</hi> for <hi>He</hi> implyes his Manhood; (and my very <hi>Oppoſites</hi> confeſſe the Soul the very Eſſence and Being of Manhood:) and <hi>[in the Day]</hi> and <hi>[ſurely dye]</hi> imply, Execution as well as Tranſgreſſion to be then; for both have equally relation to <hi>the Day: In the Day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> ſo as well may we ſay, he did not <hi>eat,</hi> as did not <hi>dye That Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if nothing dyed, that is, became mortall, but his Body; then <note n="f" place="margin">6. <hi>Abſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> that dyed, and his Soul lived; that is, muſt be as it was at firſt, before God breathed life into it; that is, a <hi>dead corps,</hi> and indeed was never other, if the Soul were a diſtinct <hi>Being</hi> of it ſelf, and all life in it ſelf, and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy but an Inſtrument to it, whereby it performeth all motion and action (as <hi>Nemeſius</hi> on <hi>Mans Nature p.</hi> 266. with others maintaine:) And thus it muſt needs follow, that this Death threatned was a meer <note n="g" place="margin">7. <hi>Abſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scar-crow,</hi> even nothing at all; for <hi>He,</hi> that is, his conſtitutive part (his Soul) continued immortall, and unchanged, and uſed his body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally, as it did before the <hi>Tranſgreſſion:</hi> and if it be Anſwered; it became ſinfull and ſubject to ſin, and ſo of finall Condemnation in Hell at the length. I Reply; That before he ſinned he was ſubject to ſin, or elſe he could not have ſinned, for <hi>quicquid est in actu, prius fuit in potentia;</hi> and if the <hi>wages of ſin be death,</hi> then he muſt be of neceſſity ſubject to <hi>death</hi> the effect, as well as ſin the cauſe at the ſame time: And ſo conſequently, the Souls poſſibility of ſinning being producted into Actuall ſin, the Soul muſt have its <hi>wages,</hi> Actuall mortality. Further, if the Soules Death be onely that of Hell; then the principall or efficient cauſe deepeſt in the Tranſgreſſion was <note n="*" place="margin">8. <hi>Abſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> leſſe puniſhed, then the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, the Body being but the Souls inſtrument whereby it acts and moves: as if a Magiſtrate ſhould hang the <hi>Hatchet,</hi> and ſpare the Man that beate a mans braines out with it: and ſo the Soul ſuffer the <hi>laſt death</hi> and ſcapethe <hi>firſt:</hi> which is as prepoſterous, as, if this <hi>Death</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">9. <hi>Abſurd.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171460:5"/> ſhould be received before this <hi>Life.</hi> Moreover: Condemnation in Hell is not properly, but remotely the reward of <hi>Adams Fall;</hi> For pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Condemnation is the wages of* <hi>Infidelity,</hi> or unbeleife in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as Salvation is of <hi>Beleife:</hi> So that none can be condemned into Hell, <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 3. 19. 36.</note> but ſuch as are actually guilty of refuſing of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> cannot be by Propagation or Succeſſion, as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality from <hi>Adam</hi> to his Iſſue; and ſo the Child though temporally, yet ſhall it not eternally be puniſhed for his Fathers ſin, but his Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall be of himſelf.</p>
               <p>Having thus from the <hi>Creation, Fall, Reſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection</hi> laid a ground-worke for this mortality, let us ſee how it commenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates with the univerſality of Scripture and Reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scriptures to prove this Mortality.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>JOb 4. 19, 21. <hi>How much leſſe on them that dwell in houſes of clay, whoſe foundation is in the duſt, which are cruſhed before the moth, doth not their excellencie which is in them goe away? they die even without Wiſdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Job 14. 1, 2. <hi>Man that is born of a woman is of few daiies, and full of trouble, he commeth up like a flower, and is cut downe; he fleeth alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not:</hi> (and ver. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. &amp; 12.) <hi>For there is hope of a Tree, if it be cut downe, that it will ſprout againe; and that the under-branch thereof will not ceaſe: though the root thereof wax old in the ground, and the ſtock thereof drie in the earth; Yet through the ſent of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it will bud, and bring forth branches like a plant. But man dieth, and waſteth away: yea man giveth up the ghoſt, and where is he? As the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters faile from the ſea, and the flood decayeth and dryeth up: So man ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe and riſeth not, till the heavens be no more, they ſhall not awake out of their ſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 103. 15. 16. <hi>As for man, his dayes are as graſſe, as a flower of the field, ſo he flouriſheth; for the wind paſſeth over it, and it is gone, and the place thereof ſhall know it no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From theſe two places compared we may ſee, that man (not his fleſh only, for that makes not man; but fleſh and ſpirit <hi>ſenſu conjuncto</hi> make Man) is not as a Tree, when he is cut downe, whoſe ſpirit liveth, and ſprouteth forth, and continueth: but as the flowre of the field, (not the ſtalke, but the bare flowre) which totally fadeth and periſheth: Therefore Man is wholly mortall: <hi>He ſhall die, and the Son of Man ſhall be made as graſſe, Iſa.</hi> 51. 12.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171460:5"/>
               <p> 2 Cor. 5. 1. 2. 3. 4. there our Being after death is called <hi>A building of an houſe not made with hands, eternall in the heavens:</hi> with this the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle deſires to be clothed: and what it is he defines, viz. <hi>mortalitie ſwallowed up of life:</hi> whence it is moſt evident, that all his hope of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life was grounded upon the Reſurrection, and that his hope was altogether grounded thereon, he confirmes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. arguing, <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, the dead ſhould not riſe:</hi> and (ver. 18.) <hi>They which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt are periſhed,</hi> and (ver. 14.) <hi>Then is our faith alſo in vaine; whoſe end</hi> (1 Pet. 1. 9.) <hi>is the ſalvation of our ſoules.</hi> How ſhould then all be in vaine, if our <hi>ſoules</hi> as ſoone as breath is out of the <note place="margin">10. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> body enter into glory and ſalvation? For by <hi>that,</hi> though there were no <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the fleſh, we ſhould receive the end of our <hi>Faith,</hi> the <hi>Salvation of our Soules:</hi> Nay further, he maketh <hi>all our hope to be in this life, if there be no Reſurrection;</hi> for <hi>ver.</hi> 19. having ſhown the evils that follow the denyall of the Reſurrection, ſaith; <hi>If in this life onely we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable:</hi> whence plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that the deniall of the Reſurrection confines all our hopes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this life, and ſo all our ſufferings, perſecutions, prayers, faith, &amp;c. were to no purpoſe: which could not be by this <hi>Soulary</hi> fancy of preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of beatitude after this life.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>David</hi> ſaith to <hi>Solomon, I go the way of all the earth:</hi> that is, as all the earth muſt ſee corruption, ſo muſt he; and if his Soul were part of him, yea, himſelf, ſo muſt it; <note n="k" place="margin">11. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> elſe ſhould he not go the way of all the earth.</p>
               <p>And the expreſſion in <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Deliver our lives from death,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth abſolute mortality: for if Death be not diſſolution of life, or its depravation, how can it be ſaid to ſuffer death? not by a bodily ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for that is but as the laying down of a burthen, wherewith it was clogged and tyred, whereby it is made more lively ten thouſand times; (as my Oppoſites confeſſe;) and ſo, can no more be ſaid to be dead, then a <note n="l" place="margin">12. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Porter</hi> when he is disburthened of his Load.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 34. 15. <hi>All fleſh ſhall periſh together, and man ſhall turne again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to duſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eccl. 3. 19. <hi>That which befalleth the Sons of Men befalleth Beaſts; even one thing befalleth them; as one dyeth, ſo dyeth the other: they have all one breath, ſo that they have no preheminence above a Beaſt: for all is vanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore if their Breath be all one, then <hi>God</hi> breathed no other Breath, (that is, life or ſoul,) into Man, then he gave to Beaſts: So
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171460:6"/> that if Man be Fallen, and the Beaſts be curſed for his ſake, Man muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> equally mortall with them.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſht my courſe, I have kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the faith, henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſſe which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall give me at THAT DAY, and not to me only, but to all them that love his love his appearing.</hi> Here from the finiſhing of his courſe a Crown being laid up, (which is even the ſame which <hi>Peter Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. 9. maketh the end of our faith, <hi>the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our ſoules)</hi> to be given at <hi>THAT DAY,</hi> concludes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion to him and us till then.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 14. 16. <hi>Keep this Commandement untill the appearing of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who only hath immortality dwelling in light, which no man can approach unto, whom no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence appeareth, that none ever entred into Heaven ſince the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: And it is in vaine for my Oppoſites to ſay it is meant of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent matter only, for they make the Soul the <hi>very manhood:</hi> and none that enter therein, enter by halfes and peecemeal: and this is confirmed by <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3 13. <hi>And no man hath aſcended into Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven, even the Son of man, which is in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>For in death there is no remembrance of thee, in the grave who ſhall give thee thanks?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89 11. 12. <hi>Shall thy loving kindneſſe be declared in the grave? or thy faithfulneſſe in deſtruction? ſhall thy wonders be known in the dark? and thy righteouſneſſe in the Land of forget fullneſſe:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38. 18. 19. <hi>For the grave cannot praiſe thee: death cannot celebrate thee: they that go down into the pit cannot hope for thy truth. The living, the living, he ſhall praiſe thee, as I do this day: the Father to the Children ſhall make known thy truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it is plain that during this Death Man is voyd of actuall Being: for had he then an incorruptible or preſent actuall Being in glory; he ſhould be more capable of the praiſe and remembrance of the Lord, then he was before he died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 3. from the 11. to 20. <hi>Why died I not from the wombe? &amp;c. for now ſhould I have lyen ſtill, and been quiet, I ſhould have ſlept, and then I ſhould have been at reſt; as a hidden untimely birth, I had not been; as Infants that never ſaw light: there the Priſoners reſt together, they heare not the voyce of the Oppreſſour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence followeth, that during this Death there is no more preſent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to man, then to an hidden abortive Embrio in this life; and no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171460:6"/> more capability, then light to unborne Infants; nor more oppreſſion or torment, then where there is none to oppreſſe: which is to ſay, He ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>IS NOT:</hi> Anſwerable to that of <hi>Iacob, me have ye bereaved of my children: Ioſeph is not, and Simeon is not, Gen.</hi> 42. 36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 4. 17. 19. 20. 21. <hi>Whoſe foundation is in the duſt, they periſh for ever:</hi> that is, ceaſe to Be till the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 37. 38. <hi>Now that the dead are raiſed &amp;c.</hi> relating to <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>I am the God of Abraham, &amp;c.</hi> From whence Chriſt proveth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: But if <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, &amp;c.</hi> had then lived in their ſoules, it had been no Argument to prove the reſurrection; for he had been the God of <hi>living</hi> ſoules <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob,</hi> though there had been no reſurrection. Beſides, he ſaith <hi>all live unto him:</hi> and this ſaying is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto the <hi>dead:</hi> therefore, as well may we argue from thence, that they lived in their bodies, as ſay, they were dead in body, but alive in ſoul unto God: for it is impoſſible to be potentially and actually living at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>Pſal. 89. 48. <hi>What man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death? ſhall he deliver his ſoul from the hand of the grave? Selah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Act. 1. 31. <hi>He ſeeing this before, ſpake of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, that his ſoul was not left in Hell, neither his fleſh did ſee corruption:</hi> whence is cleare, that ſpirit, life, breath, or ſoul are ſubject to the grave, as well as body or fleſh; for Chriſts ſoul as well as his fleſh was in Hel, that is, the grave or bonds of death: ſo that he wholy and thoroughly died for us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4. 1. 2. 3. doth ſhew, that the living ſuffer oppreſſion, but to the dead is none: and cap. 9. 45. <hi>they know not any thing; for a living Dog is better then a dead Lion:</hi> therefore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146. 2. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>I will ſing prayſes unto my God while I have any being;</hi> implying that in death is there is none: And <hi>I am.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Our life is even a vapour that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 3. <hi>every living ſoul in the Sea dyed:</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 30. 4. 5. dead ſoules <hi>lived again. And Pſal.</hi> 39. 5. <hi>man at his beſt eſtate is altogether vanity;</hi> compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 19. <hi>the creature was made ſubject to vanity;</hi> that is corruption, all which declare mans totall death. And <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. 6. 7. moſt clearly ſhew that all <hi>hope</hi> of future life and Being is in the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Thus much of Scripture, now to Naturall Reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:171460:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Naturall Reaſons to prove it: with Objections Anſwered.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IF we will rationally argue concerning the Soul, it is neceſſary to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine <hi>what that is,</hi> to which <hi>it</hi> is aſcribed: But ſince it is defined by ſome one way, by ſome another way, I ſhall produce ſome Opinions about it; and then bring the moſt rationall to tryall, omitting the more frivolous: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Stoicks</hi> held it <hi>A certaine blaſt hot and fierie:</hi> or <hi>the vitall ſpirit of the blood:</hi> The <hi>Cretians, Blood: Gallen, a certaine exhalation of the pureſt blood: Zeno, Cleanthes, Antipater,</hi> and <hi>Poſſiodonius, a hot comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, or corporeall quality diffuſed through the whole body: Democritus, Fire,</hi> and his opinion was, the <hi>round Attomes being incorporated by aire and fire doe make up the Soule: Pythagoras,</hi> opinionated it <hi>a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber moving of it ſelfe:</hi> Plato, <hi>a ſubſtance to be conceived in the mind, that received motion from it ſelfe, according to number and Harmonie:</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, <hi>the firſt continuall motion of a body naturall, having in it thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall parts, wherein was poſſibility of life:</hi> Dinarchus, <hi>an Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the four Elements:</hi> Nemeſius divides it into <hi>Phantaſie, Iudgment, Memorie:</hi> Ariſtotle in his <hi>Phyſicks,</hi> into <hi>vegetative, ſenſitive, motive, appetetive, intellective:</hi> And <hi>Ambroſe Parey,</hi> pag. 895. ſaith, <hi>the ſoule is the inward</hi> Entelechia, <hi>or the primative cauſe of all motions and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both naturall and animall, and the true Forme of a man: It ſeeth, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ſmelleth, toucheth, taſteth, imagineth, judgeth, &amp;c.</hi> And more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly <hi>pag.</hi> 83. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. he ſaith, the ſoule is commonly diſtinguiſhed into three Faculties: <hi>Animall, Vitall, Naturall:</hi> The <hi>Animall,</hi> into <hi>Principall, Senſetive, Motive:</hi> The <hi>Principall,</hi> into <hi>Imaginative,</hi> (ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the upper part of the braine) <hi>Reaſonable,</hi> (the middle part of the braine,) <hi>Memorative, (Cerebellum)</hi> or after-braine. The <hi>Senſetive,</hi> into <hi>Seeing,</hi> (the eyes) <hi>Hearing,</hi> (the eares) <hi>Smelling,</hi> (the noſe) <hi>Taſting,</hi> (the tongue, pallat) <hi>Touching,</hi> (the body) The <hi>Motive,</hi> into <hi>Progreſſive,</hi> (legs) <hi>Apprehenſive,</hi> (hands.)</p>
               <p>The <hi>Vitall,</hi> into <hi>Dilative,</hi> or parts for reſpiration, (weaſon, lungs) <hi>Concoctive,</hi> or parts for vitall motion, (heart and arteries, underſtood by the Pulſificke Facultie.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Naturall,</hi> into <hi>Nutrative, Active, Generative:</hi> which three are performed by the help of the <hi>Attractive,</hi> (the gullet) <hi>Retentive,</hi> (low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er paſſage or the ſtomack) <hi>Concoctive,</hi> (body of the ventricle) <hi>Aſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative,</hi> (three ſmall guts) <hi>Expulſive,</hi> (three great guts.)</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171460:7"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſay, it is <hi>a ſubſtance created, a ſpirit intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, inviſible, immortall, incorporeall like the Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And there be ſeverall Opinions of its Body: <hi>Lucippus</hi> and <hi>Hippar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> ſay, it hath a <hi>fierie Body: Critias</hi> and <hi>Anaxemines, Woolnor</hi> and others <hi>an aeriall body: Heſiod,</hi> an <hi>earthly: Epicurius, fierie</hi> and <hi>airie: Zenophon, watry and earthly: Drone, a middle betwixt the ſpirit and the body: Didimus</hi> and <hi>Origen, a third ſubſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Divers other conceptions and fancies there be, to uphold this ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous invention of the Soule traducted from the <hi>Heathens,</hi> who by the Book of Nature underſtood an immortality after Death; but through their ignorance how, or which way; this invention (reported to be <hi>Platoes)</hi> was occaſioned, and begat a generall beliefe: and ſo they, and after them the Chriſtians have thus ſtrained their wits to ſuch miſerable ſhifts, to define <hi>what it is,</hi> but neither conclude any certainty, or give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction therein. Yet ſince it is generally concluded to be in man, and of man; but what, where, or how no man knowes, though ſuch ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall opinions be, if but examined: Ile pitch upon thoſe which afford moſt conceptory definition: that is, that of <hi>Ariſtotle, Nemeſius,</hi> or <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe Parey,</hi> which make the Soule to be all the internall and externall Faculties of Man joyntly conſidered: or <hi>Man Anatomized:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Reply thus.</p>
               <p>All the Faculties of Man <hi>(ſenſu diviſo</hi> or <hi>conjuncto)</hi> are all, and each of them mortall; as well thoſe that are peculiar to man, as thoſe that are common to <hi>Beaſts:</hi> and if all thoſe, with his corpulent matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating Man, be proved mortall; then the invention of the Soule upon that ground vaniſheth: which I thus prove.</p>
               <p>All elementary compoſitions or Temperatures are mortall, and tranſitory:</p>
               <p>But Mans Faculties <hi>à minore ad majus</hi> are Temperatures:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Mortall.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is thus proved.</p>
               <p>That which is ſubject to <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>remiſſion</hi> is a Temperature:</p>
               <p>But all Mans Faculties, yea thoſe of <hi>Reaſon, Conſideration, Science,</hi> &amp;c. all that diſtinguiſh Man from a Beaſt, are augmented by Learning, Education, &amp;c. leſſened by Negligence, Idleneſſe, &amp;c. and quite nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Madneſſe: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That thoſe Faculties are Temperatures, I further prove thus:</p>
               <p>A Temperature is a Quality; and a Quality may be in the Subject, or abſent from it, without the deſtruction of the ſame ſubject.</p>
               <p>But Reaſon, Underſtanding, &amp;c. may be abſent from the Body their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171460:8"/> Subject, and yet the Body living: as, in mad men, and perſons in the <hi>Falling-ſickneſſe;</hi> and none will deny they are men at that ſame time: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Qualities of the Body are ſubject to ſenſe: But Vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. ſubject to none: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A hot and drie braine is quick-witted, which by moiſture and coldneſſe is altered: and ſo we are diſpoſed according to the preſent conſtitution of our Bodies.</p>
               <p>If this ſuffice not, I adde: that, an effect is by paſſion from the cauſe, as motion cannot be without paſſion from that which moveth: for take away the cauſe, and the motion ceaſeth: <hi>tolle cauſam tollitur effectus:</hi> Therefore quickneſſe of wit cannot be without paſſion from heat and dryneſſe: for over-power that hot and dry braine with moiſture and coldneſſe, as may be with <hi>Opium,</hi> and the hotneſſe and dryneſſe thereof ceaſeth, and dulneſſe followeth.</p>
               <p>Further, even from my Oppoſites Aſſertions I prove this Soul they ſo talk on, to be elementall, as <hi>Woolnor</hi> and others, who aſcribe unto it an <hi>Aeriall Body:</hi> For whatſoever is <hi>Aeriall</hi> is elementall, elſe could it not be <hi>Aeriall:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> this Soule is elementall, and ſo finite.</p>
               <p>If this immortall ſpirit have an <hi>Aeriall Body;</hi> I wonder what would become of it, if a living man were cloſed up in a Veſſell, which were ſo ſollid every where, that the Aire could not poſſibly evacuate, and there the man dye; either it muſt periſh with the man, or elſe remaine there, through which there is no paſſage for its <hi>Aeriall Body:</hi> So that he <note n="m" place="margin">13. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> ſo martyred hath an ill-favoured <hi>Paradice</hi> for his Soul.</p>
               <p>And further, experience tels us, If the former <hi>Brain-pan</hi> be hurt, the <hi>Senſes</hi> are hindred, but the <hi>Cogitation</hi> remaineth found.</p>
               <p>If onely the <hi>Middle-pan</hi> be harmed, the <hi>Cogitation</hi> is maimed; but the <hi>Seat of Senſe</hi> keeps all the <hi>five Senſes</hi> whole: If any hurt befall both to the <hi>Former</hi> and <hi>Middle-pan,</hi> both <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Cogitation</hi> decay.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Hinder-pan</hi> be diſordered only, the <hi>Memorie</hi> alone, and neither <hi>Senſe</hi> nor <hi>Cogitation</hi> receive harme.</p>
               <p>So that in veritie, Man is but a creature whoſe ſeverall parts and members are endowed with proper natures of Faculties, each ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to other, to make him a living Rationall Creature; whoſe degrees or excellencies of naturall Faculties make him in his kind more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then the Beaſts: So that though <hi>Parey</hi> and others doe ſo excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth his ſeverall endowments or properties of his ſeverall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, it doth not follow, that thoſe Faculties together are a Being of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171460:8"/> themſelves immortall: For as the members cannot be perfect mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers without them, ſo they cannot be faculties without their members; and ſeparation cannot be without deſtruction of both: As attraction or heat is the property of fire, which cannot be, if fire ceaſe; nor fire be, if it ceaſe: and as well may we ſay the heat of the fire <note n="n" place="margin">14. <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> continueth, after the fire is dead out, as thoſe Faculties when their Body is dead: for ſpoyle one, ſpoyle both; kill one, kill both; this is in that, and that is in this: The <hi>Forme</hi> is ſo in the <hi>Matter,</hi> and the <hi>Matter</hi> ſo in the <hi>Forme;</hi> as thereby, and not elſe, is an <hi>Exiſtence,</hi> or <hi>Humane Entity:</hi> And their <hi>Being</hi> is in this <hi>Vnion,</hi> and their <hi>Vnion</hi> is in this <hi>Being:</hi> So that, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Forme,</hi> and <hi>Matter</hi> ceaſeth; take away <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> ceaſeth: <hi>deſtructio vnius est interritum alterius.</hi> The <hi>Forme</hi> is the <hi>Forme</hi> of the <hi>Matter,</hi> and the <hi>Matter</hi> the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Forme;</hi> neither of themſelves but each by other, and <hi>both</hi> together make <hi>one Being:</hi> therefore if <hi>one Be</hi> by the <hi>other,</hi> and thereby <hi>Both</hi> together; then <hi>one</hi> cannot conſiſt with the <hi>other,</hi> but muſt <hi>Both</hi> periſh together: For nothing can conſiſt without that by which it is.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe on the contrary, <hi>one</hi> could conſiſt without the <hi>other,</hi> as they ſay the <hi>Soul</hi> can without the <hi>Body;</hi> then <hi>one</hi> may be generated without the <hi>other, Soul</hi> without <hi>Body,</hi> and ſo according to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous precepts, it is not unnaturall for a Woman to bring forth a <note n="o" place="margin">15. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Spirit,</hi> that hath neither fleſh, blood nor bones, inſtead of a Child.</p>
               <p>Or if <hi>one Be</hi> without the <hi>other,</hi> as <hi>Forme</hi> without <hi>Matter: Maſſe concepted,</hi> without the <hi>Facultie conceptive:</hi> then ſhould all corpulent Subſtances be as infinite as God, without beginning, <note n="p" place="margin">16. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Be</hi> of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and themſelves Gods: But I hope all grant both impoſſible: Therefore they muſt as well end together as <hi>begin</hi> together; and <hi>begin</hi> together as <hi>end</hi> together. Moreover, experience further tels us, that they neither can <hi>Be,</hi> nor conſiſt without other: For if Nature be deprived more, or leſſe in her work of conception of her due, (her <hi>Formes</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions being by her powers <hi>Formative</hi> or conceptive, or her Formed <hi>Faculties</hi> by her Facultive <hi>Formes)</hi> her Effect is accordingly: If mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brally impedited, a membrall impediment; if totally impedited, a totall fruſtration; of <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme,</hi> in <hi>Both:</hi> For he that is born without any member, hath neither <hi>Forme</hi> nor <hi>Faculty</hi> thereof at all: or with any membrall i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perfection, that part hath not its perfection either of <hi>Forme</hi> or <hi>Faculty:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o commeth it that ſome are <hi>borne Fooles,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can be wiſe: Therefore their originall <hi>Being</hi> muſt be together. And that their ultimate end is together, we ſee, that the <hi>Eye</hi> is no <hi>Eye</hi> without the <hi>Sight:</hi> and <hi>Sight</hi> no <hi>Sight</hi> without the <hi>Eye:</hi> and ſo of all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171460:9"/> the other <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Faculties è minore admajus.</hi> Wherefore, membral perfection is not ſo much in <hi>ſhape</hi> as in <hi>virtue;</hi> and <hi>virtuall perfection</hi> not ſo much in Maſſe as in due <hi>proportion,</hi> and both joyntly make <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perfection,</hi> which is the gift of <hi>God,</hi> or natures generall <hi>inſtinct:</hi> So, as one can by no meanes <hi>be</hi> without the other, ſo one cannot <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> without the other: For could there be a <hi>Facultive ſubſtance</hi> (as that of the Soul is made) without its body; then a man might live when his <note n="q" place="margin">16. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> head were cut off; yea, were his whole body quite burnt and conſumed away, except his <hi>GREAT TOE; he,</hi> even <hi>his Soul</hi> might as well live in his <hi>GREAT TOE,</hi> as before in his whole Maſſe; yea, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in that, then without all, as they childiſhly ſuppoſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore, they may as well ſay, the <hi>Popes</hi> Soul is in his <hi>GREAT TOE</hi> when men kiſſe <hi>it,</hi> as ſay, the Soul liveth, when the Body dieth. <note n="r" place="margin">17. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Further, this <hi>Facultive</hi> Gift, or Natures endowment can no more be ſaid to be a ſubſiſtent living Spirit, without its Receptacle, then the Sun-beames without the Sun, which are the gift or property of the Sun, But the Being of this communication muſt be in the Subject, as levitie in the <hi>Fire,</hi> ponderoſitie in the <hi>Earth:</hi> And though the natures of things be immediate communications of <hi>Gods Power</hi> to Nature, yet dis jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively thoſe communications are no <hi>Entities,</hi> without <hi>God</hi> be ſo many ſeverall <hi>Beings;</hi> for in that ſence they are not communications but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute <hi>Beings of themſelves;</hi> for betwixt <hi>Faculty</hi> and <hi>Subject</hi> is a <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to communication, as betwixt <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> to <hi>Fatherhood;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without other, nor it without both: and to ſay notwithſtanding, as this fancy of the <hi>Soul</hi> importeth, that there may be a <hi>Facultive Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> without its <hi>Subject;</hi> then Natures ſeverall <hi>Faculties</hi> muſt not be the ſeverall communications of <hi>One Being,</hi> but ſo many abſolute irrela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Beings of themſelves:</hi> So that this Doctrine of the <hi>Soul</hi> implyeth, <note n="ſ" place="margin">18. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> no <note n="t" place="margin">19. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>God;</hi> if a <hi>God,</hi> ſo many ſeverall <hi>Gods</hi> as <hi>Faculties:</hi> and if but <hi>ONE,</hi> then it <hi>chops</hi> 
                  <note n="v" place="margin">20. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>ONE ſmaller then hearbs to the pot:</hi> Therefore <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty</hi> ceaſeth with its <hi>Subject,</hi> or with the <hi>Subject</hi> God <hi>gathereth to himſelf</hi> the <hi>power,</hi> and yet his <hi>power</hi> no more by <hi>retraction,</hi> then leſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by <hi>communication;</hi> and ſo but <hi>One Being,</hi> in whom all things <hi>are,</hi> or one <hi>Ens Entium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, thoſe ſeverall <hi>Faculties</hi> cannot be united or comprehended in one <hi>body,</hi> but by the ſeverall members of the ſame <hi>body;</hi> for we ſee, if the member decay, the <hi>faculty</hi> decayes: Therefore their unite ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance muſt be terminated <hi>membrally</hi> in the <hi>body:</hi> And if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they could ſubſiſt ſeperated from their members; then in that ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration their <hi>Being</hi> could not be conjunct or <hi>unite,</hi> for want of that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171460:9"/> which tyed them together, <hi>the ſeverall members:</hi> And ſo, if any <hi>Being,</hi> ſo many ſeverall <hi>Beings</hi> as ſeverall <hi>Faculties:</hi> if any <hi>Soul,</hi> ſo many <note n="w" place="margin">21. <hi>Abſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Soules:</hi> a <hi>Phantaſticke Soul,</hi> a <hi>Rationall Soul,</hi> a <hi>Memorative Soul,</hi> a <hi>Seeing Soul,</hi> a <hi>Hearing Soul,</hi> a <hi>Smelling Soul,</hi> a <hi>Taſting Soul,</hi> a <hi>Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soul,</hi> with divers other <hi>Souls</hi> of all ſorts, and ſizes: as, <hi>ſaving your preſence,</hi> an <note n="x" place="margin">22. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Evacuating Soul,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And further, that thoſe <hi>Faculties</hi> are thus in their <hi>Subjects,</hi> and are not without them, (as <hi>accidens non eſt niſi in ſubjecto)</hi> we ſee, that they increaſe and grow with their <hi>Subjects,</hi> and perfect together: For a Child is totally proportionated (as <hi>Adam</hi> when <hi>God formed</hi> him of the Earth) before the <hi>vitall Faculty</hi> be actuall, (as <hi>Parey</hi> ſaith) and the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall</hi> requireth a due proceſſe of time after birth, before it be ripe to bring forth the fruit of <hi>Rationality,</hi> &amp; as its <hi>Subject</hi> groweth and ripeneth, ſo it increaſeth and perfecteth: for it is impoſſible, that the thing which is not actual in it ſelf, ſhould have a ſecond thing actuall in it; and <hi>Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onality</hi> in an Infant, is no more in it, then a <hi>Chickin</hi> in the <hi>egge,</hi> only in <hi>poſſe:</hi> therefore a Child cannot poſſibly <hi>ratiocinate,</hi> before it be actually <hi>Rationall;</hi> which cannot be before <hi>Organnicall</hi> perfection: For <hi>Reaſon</hi> cannot <hi>Be,</hi> and not ſhew it ſelf; ſhew it ſelf and not <hi>Be;</hi> for its <hi>Being</hi> is its <hi>Rationality,</hi> and its <hi>Rationality</hi> its <hi>Being:</hi> therefore as its <hi>Organs</hi> are <hi>potentiall,</hi> it is <hi>potentiall;</hi> and as its <hi>Organs</hi> are weake and <hi>imperfect,</hi> it is weak and <hi>imperfect;</hi> and as they are <hi>perfect,</hi> it is <hi>perfect:</hi> Therefore <hi>Faculties</hi> increaſe with their <hi>Subjects,</hi> and if increaſe, they muſt decreaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anatomize</hi> Man, Take a view of all his <hi>Lineaments</hi> and <hi>Dimenſions,</hi> of all his <hi>members</hi> and <hi>Faculties,</hi> and conſider their ſtate ſeverally, and all are tranſitory, even all that goeth to the <hi>Subject Man</hi> is corruptible, and himſelf but a Bundle of corruption, or curious Maſſe of vicilitudes. If all of Man that goeth to his <hi>Manhood</hi> be mortall, where then, or what is this immortall thing the <hi>Soul</hi> they talke of? we have examined all his <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>faculties,</hi> and find even all mortall: It is not ſure his <hi>prima materia</hi> though <hi>ingenerable, incorruptible, inſenſible, indefinite,</hi> &amp;c. Nor his <hi>Forma prima,</hi> that principle which firſt gives <hi>Eſſence</hi> to a naturall <hi>Body;</hi> the firſt Active principle, <hi>informing</hi> and figurating the <hi>Firſt Matter, ſui appetentem;</hi> for both are generall to the <hi>whole Creation,</hi> whoſe <hi>Efficient Cauſe</hi> is onely immediately <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, by whoſe power all things that are made ſhall be returned to that of which they were made, their <hi>Materia prima,</hi> or created matter: So that, (as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith,) <hi>Man hath no preheminence above a Beaſt, even one thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falleth them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Reaſon is there now, that <hi>Mans Faculties</hi> in a higher Degree,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171460:10"/> ſhould be an immortall Spirit, more then a <hi>Beaſts</hi> in a lower degree? but both elementary and finite.</p>
               <p>Further, if it be not unnaturall that <hi>Seeing, Hearing,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be producted by an <hi>Elementary operation,</hi> as none deny in the propagation of <hi>Beaſts:</hi> why is not the <hi>rationall facultie</hi> in <hi>Man</hi> as naturall in <hi>Man,</hi> and may as well be producted <hi>elementarily</hi> by <hi>Man,</hi> as the other by <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and be as actually mortall? If this ſuffice not, obſerve; <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia non recipit majus aut minus,</hi> a <hi>Giant</hi> is no more a man then a <hi>Dwarfe:</hi> there may be a graduall diſtinction, and yet no <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; Degrees of <hi>Faculties</hi> in ſeverall perſons, and yet the <hi>Faculties</hi> the ſame, and of one nature, though not equally excellent: and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree doth not make a <hi>Facultie</hi> more a <hi>Facultie,</hi> or leſſe a <hi>Facultie:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if the ſaid <hi>Faculties</hi> in an inferiour Degree be elementary, ſo muſt they in a ſuperiour: But in <hi>Brutes,</hi> whom none deny to be wholly mortall, and all their <hi>Faculties</hi> elementary, have our moſt noble parts and <hi>Faculties</hi> ſcattered amongſt them, though in an inferiour degree: As <hi>Ambroſe Parey</hi> ſaith, <hi>(Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) <hi>If we will diligently ſearch into their nature, we ſhall obſerve the impreſſions of many virtues: as, of Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity, Prudence, Fortitude, Clemency, Docility, Love, Carefulneſſe, Providence;</hi> yea, <hi>Knowledge, Vnderſtanding, Memory,</hi> &amp;c. is common to all <hi>Brutes;</hi> the <hi>Affections</hi> and <hi>Paſſions</hi> of the Mind, all his <hi>Qualities</hi> good and bad, and every <hi>Facultie</hi> he hath is to be found more or leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: And <hi>Parey</hi> further ſaith, <hi>They are of quicke ſenſe, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Rites of Friendſhip and Chaſtity, they ſubmit themſelves to the Diſcipline of Man, they have taught Man many things,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hare</hi> is eminent for <hi>Memory,</hi> the <hi>Dog</hi> for <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity,</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> for <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> the <hi>Fox</hi> for <hi>Subtiltie,</hi> the <hi>Dove</hi> for <hi>Chaſtity</hi> and <hi>Innocency,</hi> the <hi>Elephant</hi> for <hi>Docility, Modeſty,</hi> and <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi> Plinie ſaith, <hi>he commeth neare the understanding of a man, that they worſhip the Moon and Stars:</hi> Plutarch, <hi>that they worſhip the Sunriſing.</hi> The <hi>Ape</hi> is eminent for <hi>Imitation</hi> and <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> the <hi>Turtle</hi> for <hi>Love,</hi> the <hi>Crocodile</hi> for <hi>Deceit,</hi> the <hi>Lambe</hi> for <hi>Patience,</hi> the <hi>Waſpe</hi> for <hi>Anger,</hi> &amp;c. and for his <hi>Five Senſes</hi> he is by them exceld.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Aper auditu nos vincit, Aranea tactu,</l>
                  <l>Vultur odoratu, Linx viſu, Simia guſtu.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus Man <hi>in ſenſu diviſo</hi> is to be found amongſt the other <hi>Creatures,</hi> and in him alone thoſe ſeverall <hi>Faculties</hi> are eminent <hi>ſenſu conjuncto,</hi> and ſo only capable of God: Therfore thoſe <hi>Faculties</hi> being elementary in an inferiour Degree, in an inferiour Creature, why may they not be elementary in a ſuperiour Degree in a ſuperiour Creature?</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:171460:10"/>
               <p> Now from all, this followeth, that if in man be an immortali ſpirit, then divers other Creatures have the like, though not in the ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; for if Degree therein ſhould make or mar the thing it ſelfe, then ſome <note n="y" place="margin">23. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> would have no more <hi>Soules</hi> then Beaſts, and ſome leſſe: as <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> and <hi>Fooles</hi> no more; and <hi>Infants</hi> leſſe. If it be the <hi>Rationall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie,</hi> then all men are borne without <hi>Soules,</hi> 
                  <note n="z" place="margin">24. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> and ſome die <note n="a" place="margin">25. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> before they had <hi>Soules,</hi> as <hi>Infants;</hi> and ſome after <note n="b" place="margin">26. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> their <hi>Soules</hi> are gone, as <hi>Mad-men</hi> that live and periſh in their <hi>madneſſe;</hi> and ſome <note n="c" place="margin">27. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> would be borne, live, and die without <hi>Soules,</hi> as <hi>Fooles;</hi> and ſome <note n="d" place="margin">28. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> would have <hi>Soules</hi> but by <hi>fits</hi> and <hi>jumps,</hi> as <hi>Drunkards,</hi> perſons with the <hi>Falling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſickneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. nay all of us ſpend a great part of our dayes without our <hi>Soules,</hi> for while we are in ſound ſleep our Rationality ceaſeth <hi>pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore:</hi> Thus this Immortall Spirit goes and comes as occaſion ſerves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objections from Naturall Reaſons Anſwered.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEcauſe I have onely met with one or two in this kind, I ſhall give a glance upon them, and paſſe to thoſe <hi>Objections</hi> which are extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Scripture,</hi> which are various.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object. Wooln. pag.</hi> 324.</label> 
                  <hi>If the Soul be compounded of the Elements, it will not follow, that it muſt needs be mortall; becauſe Corruption and Death comes not onely, nor ſo much from Propagation or Compoſition, as from divine Malediction: for</hi> the wages of ſin is death: <hi>Without which even</hi> Adams <hi>Body ſhould have been immortall as well as his Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer. The Soule (by his owne grounds) was chiefly, the body but inſtrumentally in the Tranſgreſſion: And ſo, if the wages of ſin be death, the Soule was under the divine Malediction as well as the Body: ſo that it (if ſuch a thing be) loſt its ſupernaturality and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, as well as the body: Therefore, if by this Rule the Souls Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality may be pleaded, much <note n="e" place="margin">29. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> more may the Bodies.</p>
               <p>I ſhould (according to the import of the Title of this Chapter) have produced more Objections in this kind: but finding Naturall Reaſon ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent therein, I Anſwer ſuch ſilent ones with ſilence. Needs muſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be ſilent in the defence of this fancie, ſince it cannot define what that is, to which this immortality is aſcribed: Yet ſome beyond all Reaſon to uphold this ignote endleſſe entitie, ſay, that though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be defined what it is, yet it followeth not that it <hi>is</hi> not: as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not define what God is, yet it followeth not that there is no God: And ſo it mattereth not whether it be the <hi>Rationall Facultie,</hi> or no; or what it <hi>is,</hi> ſo long as it <hi>is.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171460:11"/>
               <p> To this I Anſwer, That this is to make no diſtinction betwixt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Madneſſe; As if we were bound to beleeve that, for which there is no ſenſe nor reaſon; ſo might we beleeve there were ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Gods, yea blocks and ſtones were Gods ſufficient to ſave: But we find in Scripture and in Nature ſufficient to convince our Reaſons that there is but one God, and he that one whom we worſhip, though our Reaſons are not able fully to comprehend him; ſo much of him wee know, as our Reaſons is able to containe: whereas for this immortall ſpirit, there is not ſo much of it declared as may convince Reaſon what it <hi>is,</hi> or that it <hi>is;</hi> and to beleeve that it <hi>is,</hi> becauſe we cannot know what it <hi>is,</hi> ſhall be no Article of my Beliefe.</p>
               <p>Thus proved from Scripture and Reaſon, let us proceed to the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of what from Scripture ſhall be obtruded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objections extorted from Scripture Anſwered.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <label>OBject. 1.</label> 
                  <hi>Therefore we are alwayes confident, knowing that whilſt we are at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord: we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident I ſay, and willing rather, to be abſent from the body, and to be preſent with the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 6. 8.</p>
               <p>Whence is inferred a preſent injoyment of Glory immediately after death.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, that both the foregoing and ſubſequent matter deny ſuch an Interpretation, or Conſequence: for before, wiſhing to be <hi>clothed with our Houſe from Heaven,</hi> on which is this expreſſion of <hi>being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord,</hi> he expounds, that his meaning is thereby, <hi>that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality might be ſwallowed up of life,</hi> or as he ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 53. <hi>that this corruptible</hi> (man) <hi>might put on incorruption, and this mortall put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality:</hi> And the following matter of them words, being laid down as the reaſon or ground why he ſo ſpake, prove, that by his <hi>[preſence with the Lord,]</hi> he meant nothing elſe, but his ſtate after the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for ſaith he, <hi>we muſt all appear before the judgment ſeat of Chriſt, that every one, &amp;c. ver.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obj. 2.</label> 
                  <hi>For I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better; nevertheleſſe, to abide in the fleſh is much needfull for you, Phil.</hi> 1. 23. 24.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer: this is of the ſame nature, therefore muſt have the ſame Interpretation: for <hi>Paul</hi> did not preach one thing to the Philippians, and the contrary to the Corinthians. Beſides, ſuch manner of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171460:11"/> are not contradictory to this mortality; for though there be long time to the <hi>Living</hi> till the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> there is none to the <hi>Dead:</hi> for <note place="margin">Pſa. 39. 13</note> from <hi>Adams death</hi> to his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> at the end of the World, will be to him, as the twinkling of an eye to the Living; yea, the twinkling of an eye to the living, is more time, then a thouſand, yea ten thouſand yeares is to the dead: For <hi>Being</hi> onely commenſurates with Time, or length of dayes; <hi>not to Be</hi> cannot poſſibly be capable thereof: So, that the <hi>Livings</hi> tedious <hi>anniverſary</hi> expectation of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>end of their faith;</hi> is not a <hi>twinkling</hi> to the <hi>grave:</hi> the Livings <hi>Future</hi> is the Deads <hi>Preſent:</hi> Therefore, it is well figurated in Scripture by <hi>ſleep,</hi> as <hi>ſlept with his fathers,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 43. <hi>falne aſleep in Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 18. &amp;c. not that it is ſo long a time to the dead, but that in nature there is nothing ſo repreſents death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or <hi>non-being,</hi> as <hi>ſleep:</hi> So that this may take away all carnall ſecurity; for who would not watch and pray over night, that knowes he muſt die in the morning? live well and be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to day, that muſt <hi>riſe</hi> and <hi>anſwer</hi> to morrow; beleeve to day, that would not be <hi>damned,</hi> but <hi>ſaved</hi> to morrow: This adminiſters comfort to the righteous, but terrour to the wicked.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 3.</label> 
                  <hi>And it came to paſſe as her ſoule was in departing, Gen.</hi> 35. 18. Ergo, there is ſuch a thing as the Soule, which continueth its Being after death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> No ſuch matter; for the ſenſe of the words is, <hi>as ſhe was dying,</hi> or <hi>life a departing,</hi> for the following words ſay <hi>ſhe dyed;</hi> which could not be, if her ſoule (her conſtitutive part) lived ſtill, no more then a man can be ſaid to loſe his hand, when he loſes a finger.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 4.</label> 
                  <hi>And he ſtretched himſelfe upon the Child three times, and cryed unto the Lord, and ſaid, O Lord my God, pray thee, let this Childs ſoule come into him againe: And the Lord heard his voice, and the ſoule of the Child came into him again, and he revived.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17. 21. 22. And <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. 22. it is ſaid, <hi>his fleſh upon him ſhall have pain, and his ſoule within him ſhall mourne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo, there is ſuch a thing as the ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſ.</label> If it be meant <hi>life</hi> or <hi>breath,</hi> whoſe <hi>Being</hi> is conſiſtent and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in a corpulent union: For, by that of the <hi>Child,</hi> is meant his breath or life, the thing that his corpulent matter wanted; as <hi>ver.</hi> 17. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth, which ſaith, <hi>his ſickneſſe was ſo ſore, that there was no breath left in him:</hi> Therefore, that which was gone, was prayed for, his <hi>breath</hi> or <hi>life,</hi> as his Anſwer further proveth, which was, <hi>and it revived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by <hi>Soul</hi> in that of <hi>Iob</hi> is meant, his <hi>conſcience;</hi> whoſe ſeat is in the <hi>reaſonable</hi> and <hi>memorative Faculties.</hi> Therefore, the uſe of the word
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171460:12"/> 
                  <hi>Soule</hi> in thoſe places, doe not prove ſuch a thing in man as is ſuppoſed: For in Scripture it is variouſly uſed upon various occaſions. It is put for the <hi>ſtomack, Prov.</hi> 27. 4. for the <hi>eyes, Ier.</hi> 13: 17. for the <hi>heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. for <hi>God, Prov.</hi> 9. 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 38. <hi>Ier.</hi> 14. 17. for the <hi>dead body, Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. for the <hi>whole man, Levit.</hi> 7. 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Num.</hi> 15. 39. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 46. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41. 1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 3. 20. for <hi>breath, Act.</hi> 20. 10. for <hi>life, Iſa.</hi> 53. 17.</p>
               <p>Therefore, from thoſe places thoſe parts may as well be proved ſo many Soules, or Spirits of Immortality, as from thoſe where it is put for <hi>Breath</hi> or <hi>Life,</hi> its <hi>Being</hi> be proved, or ſuch an immortall exiſtence to be in the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 5.</label> 
                  <hi>For which cauſe we faint not; for though our outward man periſh, yet the inward is renewed day by day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> there is ſoule and body in man.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> It is not ſaid, <hi>Though our fleſh periſh, yet our ſoules is renewed;</hi> then 'twere ſomething to little purpoſe, but it is ſaid, <hi>our outward man,</hi> which compared with what is meant by <hi>inward man,</hi> muſt needs be whole man; for by <hi>inward man</hi> is meant faith or work of grace, <hi>(Rom.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17.) which is no part of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man: ſo that without it or its renewing we are men perfect, as well as with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 6.</label> 
                  <hi>Who knoweth the ſpirit of man, that goeth upward; and the ſpirit of a beaſt that goeth downward to the earth? Wherefore man hath a ſoule that goeth preſently to Heaven, but the beaſts to the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> It cannot beare that ſenſe; for immediately before he ſaith, <hi>their breath is all one, there is no difference, as the one dyeth ſo dyeth the other, and goeth to one place,</hi> the <hi>duſt:</hi> Therefore, if the beaſts be rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the elements, ſo muſt mans. The meaning I take to be thus, that ſuch a wonderfull thing is the breath of a man, that breatheth upward, and the breath of a beaſt tkat breatheth downward, (for <hi>Spirit</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth breath) according to that of <hi>Ovid:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pronaque cum ſpectent animalia caetera terram,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Os Homini ſublime dedit,</hi> coelumque <hi>videre</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iuſſit, &amp; erectos ad ſidera tollere vultus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> that its Faculty how it <hi>is,</hi> is paſt finding out: for Art in all her imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions could never touch that ſecret with her penſill.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 7.</label> 
                  <hi>Feare not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule, but rather feare him, who is able to deſtroy both ſoule and body in hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This carryes the face indeed of the ſoules immortality: but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171460:12"/> if the interpretation muſt be confined to that ſence, it overthrowes the current of the whole <hi>Scriptures:</hi> Wherefore, my opinion of it is, that by [not able to kill the ſoul] is meant, (as <hi>Luke</hi> hath it, <hi>c.</hi> 12. 4) <hi>have no more that they can do:</hi> that is, though they have power over this life, which is <hi>ſowen in corruption,</hi> they have none over that which is <hi>rayſed in incorruption, But rather feare him which is able to deſtroy both ſoul and body in Hell;</hi> that, (as <hi>Luke hath it,) after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into Hell.</hi> This doth not ſet forth any immortality before the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> but ſhewes, that onely that is in Gods hand, and he onely able to touch it, that is, <hi>caſt it into Hell.</hi> That this muſt be ſo expounded, I further prove from the <hi>non-entity</hi> of Hell; for there can be no caſting into Hell, before Hell be, which though it be <hi>ordained of old, Iſa.</hi> 30. 33. <note place="margin">No Hell till the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</note> it is but in <hi>poſſe,</hi> not in <hi>eſſe</hi> till the Reſurrection: For ſatisfaction, it is convenient to declare what we mean by Hell: for Hell is diverſly uſed in Scripture: It is put for the <hi>grave, Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 55. 15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 15. for the <hi>Whale</hi> in which <hi>Ionah</hi> was, <hi>Ion.</hi> 2. 2. for <hi>Sathans</hi> Kingdom lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Hell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18. for <hi>Satan,</hi> or his malignant ſpirits, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 6. for the place of the damned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 29. &amp; 10. 28. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 5. &amp; 16. 23. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. and this laſt, [the place of the damned] is that which we meane by Hell: and it is likewiſe variouſly called: as, <hi>outer darkneſſe, Mat.</hi> 22. 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. 33. <hi>wrath to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. 9. <hi>Chaines of darkeneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Iude</hi> 6. <hi>eternall fire, Iude</hi> 23. <hi>ſecond death, Rev.</hi> 20. 16. <hi>bottomleſſe pit, Rev.</hi> 9. 2. <hi>the place of torment, Rev.</hi> 14. 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. 10. <hi>Lake of fire, Rev.</hi> 29. 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. 8. <hi>everlaſting puniſhment, Mat.</hi> 25. 41. 46. <hi>blackneſſe and darkneſſe for ever, Iude</hi> 13. Thoſe ſeverall expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are generally taken to ſet forth the end of the Reprobate, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of Gods wrath upon them: Therefore, if none of the formenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned places that Hell is put for, ſave that of the place of the damned, be taken for Hell, then moſt of thoſe ſeverall expreſſions ſuite with it: but the expreſſions in generall grant no immediate execution after this death, but imply the contrary, as we may ſee, if we examine them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 13. where it is called <hi>outer darkneſſe,</hi> and 23. v. 33. <hi>damnation of Hell,</hi> compared with <hi>cap.</hi> 25. 41. where it is ſaid, <hi>Then ſhall he ſay unto them on the left hand, depart from me yee curſed into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire prepared for the Divel and his Angels:</hi> to this adde 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>For we muſt all appeare before the Iudgment Seate of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in the fleſh, whether good or evil:</hi> and to theſe adde 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 10. &amp; 5. 9. where it is called, <hi>wrath to come:</hi> which thus compared ſhew plainely, it is to come; elſe execution muſt go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Judgment, which in a Common-wealth would be ridiculous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171460:13"/>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">29. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> as firſt to hang men, and then judge them. At the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we all muſt receive our reward according to our deeds good or bad, <hi>THEN ſhall he ſay unto them on his left hand &amp;c.</hi> and not before <hi>THEN:</hi> for it cannot be twice received: therefore, it is fitly called <hi>wrath to come;</hi> and the very <hi>divels</hi> confirme this themſelves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 25. <hi>art thou come to torment us before the time?</hi> which proveth plainly, that the time of their torment was not come: and if the <hi>Divel</hi> cannot be believed, <hi>God</hi> further cleares it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>For if he ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to Hell, and delivered them into Chaines of darkeneſſe, to be reſerved unto Iudgment.</hi> And <hi>Iude</hi> 6. <hi>The Angels which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habitation, he hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in everlaſting Chaines, unto the Iudgment of the great day:</hi> In both which places it is ſaid, they are <hi>reſerved unto Iudgment:</hi> and <hi>Iude ver.</hi> 7. <hi>to the Reprobate is reſerved the blackeneſſe for ever:</hi> and to this adde <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 10. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. which clearly ſhew, that at the day of Judgement both Divels and Reprobate together ſhall be caſt into the <hi>Lake of fire:</hi> Therefore, if reſerved for both till then, Ile be bold to ſay, it ſhall not be till, nor before <hi>then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 20. it is ſaid, <hi>the beaſt and the falſe Prophet and them that worſhipped his image were caſt alive into the lake of fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone:</hi> and <hi>c.</hi> 20. 10. <hi>And the Devil that deceived them, was caſt into the Lake:</hi> and this <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. is called <hi>the ſecond death:</hi> therefore, this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting into the Lake muſt be after the <hi>Fall</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and after he hath done <hi>deceiving;</hi> and not before; for if he be there now, he hath done <hi>deceiving;</hi> for once there, it is impoſſible he ſhould <hi>deceive:</hi> but that he hath not, there is more witneſſes, then ſtars in the Skie, or ſands in the Sea; <hi>our innumerable ſinnes,</hi> whoſe juſt reward is the <hi>ſecond death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be Queſtioned, where then the Divels are?</p>
               <p>Obſerve, they are but Creatures, and ſuch as are fallen from their <hi>Heavenly manſions;</hi> therefore, within the <hi>Sublunary</hi> compaſſe, ſo that as the Earth is the proper place for ponderous and groſſe bodies: and the Devils being more ſubtile and aiereal may be referred to the air; and not without ground from <hi>Scripture:</hi> for <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 2. the Devil is called <hi>the Prince of the power of the aire:</hi> ſo that their caſting into Hell, muſt be the aire: and Hell may as well be put for the aire in thoſe places, as in other for the grave, &amp;c. their <hi>priſon,</hi> or place of cuſtody, as the grave to the dead. And <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 9. tis ſaid, <hi>he was caſt into the earth, and his Angels &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This premiſed, <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> not yet; well might ignorance ſtraine it ſelf into ſuch incertaine conceits about the place of it's Being,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171460:13"/> and it not as yet: Some have feigned it in <hi>Mount Aetna,</hi> ſome in the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fire,</hi> which is betwixt the <hi>upper region</hi> of the <hi>Aire</hi> and the <hi>Globe</hi> of the <hi>Moon;</hi> ſome to be in the <hi>Caves of the Earth,</hi> and <hi>Conduits of the Sea;</hi> ſome only in the <hi>Sea,</hi> as <hi>Archer</hi> in his <hi>Perſonall raigne of Chriſt</hi> mentions, becauſe the Divels were caſt into the <hi>Swine,</hi> which <hi>ran vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently down a ſteopplace into the Sea. Mar.</hi> 5. 3. ſurely, they might as wel ſay, they have <note n="f" place="margin">30. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> Milſtones about their necks, becauſe it is alſo ſaid, <hi>better a milſtone were tyed about his neck, and he caſt into the bottome of the Sea:</hi> for the one followeth no more then the other: Some ſay, it is in the earth equally ſo far diſtant from the ſurface, as Heaven is above it: as <hi>Phillips,</hi> &amp;c. and this he labours to confirme with <hi>Scripture:</hi> as, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 4. <hi>The way of life is above to the wiſe, that he may depart from Hell beneath.</hi> and <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>That in the name of Ieſus every knee ſhould bow, of things in Heaven, and things in Earth, and things under the Earth: i. e.</hi> in Hell ſaith he. And <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>The rich man ſaw Abraham a far off, and Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus in his boſome:</hi> And <hi>Ezek.</hi> 31. 18. <hi>Yet ſhalt thou be brought down with the Trees of Eden unto the nether parts of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thoſe and ſuch like places which literally ſeem to import Hell, conclude the thing no more, then other literall expreſſions prove God to have corpulent eyes, eares, hands, &amp;c. but are expreſſions after the manner of men, to ſhew the gradation of condition betwixt the wicked and the righteous, the one the extreameſt debaſement, the other the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt exaltation, which could not be better figurated to ſence, then by Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>And in particular thus: The firſt, as <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 24. is litterall or figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, which interpretation can neither be <hi>canonicall</hi> nor <hi>rationall;</hi> for thereby wiſe men muſt not tread upon the <note n="g" place="margin">31. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> ground, but muſt walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Aire,</hi> or upon the <hi>water,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> upon the <hi>Sea, (Mat.</hi> 14. 25. 29.) and there only the way of life: for it ſaith, <hi>their way is above,</hi> For the ſecond; as, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10. that is both <hi>propheticall</hi> and <hi>figurative,</hi> to ſhew how in proceſſe of time all Degrees ſhall ſubject to <hi>Chriſt: Angels, Men, Beaſts, Devils,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> whoſe Degrees is thus literally expreſſed to ſence by <hi>Heaven, Earth, under the Earth;</hi> or <hi>Angels</hi> that are higheſt in dignity, and ſo coeleſtiall; <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>ſublunars</hi> the midle, and ſo terreſtriall; <hi>Divels</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> the loweſt, and ſo ſubterreſtriall.</p>
               <p>The third, as <hi>Luke</hi> 16. is <hi>parabolicall:</hi> (of which more anon) and it ſeemes by this, if Hell be ſo deep in the Earth, <note n="h" place="margin">32. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Damned</hi> have won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull good eyes, to ſee through the earths groſſe body, and the Heavens 12. Spheares into the Coelum Empyreum, to ſpy <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:171460:14"/> boſome; or elſe Heaven muſt be there too, even in the centure of the Earth: this is the conſequence of ſuch <hi>parabollicall</hi> Arguments. And the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. or laſt, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 31. 18. is a kin to thoſe: for it is but to ſhew, how that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the height of his pride and fury was brought to confuſion, which in the 15. <hi>v.</hi> is expreſſed by, <hi>In the day when he went down into the grave,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>unto death to the nether parts of the earth, to the pit;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>into Hell:</hi> all which ſhew but the ſudden death, and utter confuſion of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Army: and at the utmoſt, Hell here can be but put for death, or the grave, and not for any ſuch place of torment.</p>
               <p>There is yet an other Opinion of the place of Hell, which is the beſt that ever I heard or read of, and that is (according to <hi>Archers</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) the Earth reduced to its <hi>prima materia</hi> or <hi>created matter,</hi> which he ſaith cannot be conſumed, and there ſhall the Damned be caſt: But leaſt I ſhould dive further in the inquiſition of the place then my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion will reach, Ile leave it to the wofull experience of the <hi>damned</hi> at the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 8.</label> 
                  <hi>ſuch a one caught up into the third Heavens: how that he was caught up into Paradice,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 2. 4. <hi>there Paradice is put for the third Heavens: And to this compare Chriſts Anſwer to the theife upon the Croſſe: This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradice: Therefore, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice is the third Heavens, the place for the ſouls of the righteous, whither the Theifes ſoul went that day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Firſt, Chriſt was not there that day himſelf; for his humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was three dayes and three nights in the grave after his death.</p>
               <p>2ly, His whole humanity (ſoul and body as 'tis called) ſuffered death, as it was neceſſary, for if his body only ſuffered, what ſhould our ſouls have done for a Redeemer? (of this more hereafter) ſo that the ſaying of the prophet is fulfilled: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. <hi>For thou wilt not leave my ſoul in Hell,</hi> (i. e. his manhood in the grave) <hi>nor ſuffer thine holy One to ſee corruption:</hi> i. e. or there to putrifie.</p>
               <p>3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, If ſo; then the ſouls of the righteous have an earthly fading habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for the 12. Spheares are as the earth is a meer elementall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſation; and <hi>at the Day of the Lord the Heavens ſhall paſſe away with a great noyſe, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat:</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 10. But their habitation is of <hi>a better and enduring ſubſtance, Heb.</hi> 10. 13. <hi>eternall,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled, and that fadeth not away,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. whereas, this makes it mortall, corruptible, and fading: ſo that, the ſoul changeth but one corruptible earthly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for an other, that ſhall fleet away, and <hi>no more place ſhall be found for it, Rev.</hi> 10. 20. and 21. 1.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171460:14"/>
               <p> 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the firſt fruits of them that ſlept, and thereby (as he tould his Diſciples) he went to prepare a place for them in his Fathers houſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore if it were then to <hi>prepare,</hi> it was not then in <hi>eſſe,</hi> there could be none in, before it ſelf was in <hi>Being:</hi> ſo that if <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, &amp;c.</hi> as ſoon as they died, entred preſently therein, it is as if we ſhould be actually in a Houſe before the Houſe be built, or enjoy the Purchaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Price be paid, or Poſſeſſion had.</p>
               <p>I may (and not without ground) poſitively affirme, that the place of Glory for the dead Saints is not yet: and ſhall not actually <hi>Be</hi> till the <note place="margin">Heaven o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the place of glory for the Saints not till the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> diſſolution of thoſe Heavens and this earth, according to that of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65. 15. <hi>For behold I create New Heavens and a New Earth, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſhall not be remembered, nor come into mind.</hi> Chap. 66. <hi>the New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the New earth ſhall remaine before me ſaith the Lord.</hi> And 2 Pet. 3. 12. tis ſaid, <hi>we look for New Heavens and a New Earth,</hi> (after the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the old <hi>ver.</hi> 12.) <hi>wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe.</hi> And <hi>Iohn</hi> after he had revealed the end and finall diſſolution of the world, and the Judgment of the quick and dead; ſaith, <hi>And I ſaw a New Heaven, and a New Earth; for the firſt Heaven and the firſt Earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>&amp;c. And I ſaw the holy City,</hi> &amp;c. Whence is obſervable, that <hi>Iſaiah, Peter,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> with one conſent in probation that they did not meane any ſtate in this world, expreſly conclude the diſſolution of thoſe Heavens &amp; this earth, before their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie be fulfilled. 2ly, that they are not the ſame with thoſe, they ſtile them <hi>New,</hi> to diſtinguiſh them from the old. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, that they intend no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation of the old, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> maketh them a work of <hi>Creation: [I create New Heavens &amp;c.]</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, to confirme it further, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> declareth their eternity, <hi>[the New Heavens and the New Earth ſhall continue before me ſaith the Lord]</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, <hi>Peter</hi> maketh them pure and undefiled: <hi>[wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe]</hi> And into this <hi>New Earth Iohn ſaw the holy City, New Ieruſalem comming down from God out of Heaven,</hi> (ver. 2.) <hi>and heard a voyce out of Heaven, ſaying, Behold, the Tabernacle of God with men, and he will dwell with them. ver.</hi> 3. and <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth:</hi> whence it is moſt certaine, that it ſhall never be defiled with ſin, <hi>for the glory of God ſhall lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof, ver.</hi> 23. <hi>and they ſhall raigne for ever and ever. cap.</hi> 22. 5. 6<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, there ſhall be no <hi>teares,</hi> no <hi>death,</hi> nor <hi>ſorrow,</hi> nor <hi>any more paine: for the former things are paſſed away. cap.</hi> 21. 4. none of all which is computable with the ſtate of this world: but if compared with thoſe places which ſpeake of the ſtate of glory or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171460:15"/> for the Saints that <hi>ſleep in Chriſt,</hi> after this life: as, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. where it is made <hi>an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled, and that fadeth not away.</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 34. it is called <hi>an enduring ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 11. 14. it is called a <hi>Countrey,</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>an heavenly Countrey:</hi> which ſo anſwer and correſpond with this <hi>New Creation,</hi> that thereto only it is computable: therefore, they muſt needs be one and the ſame; and that they are, the propheſies themſelves do witneſſe, as, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 24. <hi>the Nations of them that are ſaved ſhall walk in the light of it:</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 22. 5. <hi>there they ſhall raigne for ever and for ever:</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> makes it the end of their faith, ſaying, <hi>we according to his promiſe look for new Heavens</hi> &amp;c. and further to confirme it, compare <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 14. 15. 16. 17. with <hi>cap.</hi> 20. 1. 2. 3 4. and you ſhall find, that it ſhall be the reward of thoſe that <hi>come out of tribulation</hi> &amp;c. Therefore, this is <hi>the inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled &amp;c.</hi> the <hi>purchaſed poſſeſſion, Ephe.</hi> 1. 14. the <hi>World to come, ver.</hi> 21. the <hi>reward</hi> and <hi>end of our faith.</hi> This being thus, it is impoſſible, that any ſhould injoy that for the preſent, which is yet to create: So that the <hi>Thiefe</hi> is found a <hi>World</hi> too ſhort of this <hi>Paradice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> Peter ſaith, it is reſerved in Heaven.</p>
               <p>To that and ſuch like expreſſions I Anſwer, that the word <hi>Heaven</hi> being fitteſt to expreſſe the highneſſe of its degree, and exaltation of its glory to ſence, is uſed for no other end: ſo that the meaning is, <hi>reſerved in higheſt dignity:</hi> for <hi>Heaven</hi> in Scripture is oftentimes uſed, to expreſſe the height and dignity of a thing, as, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> Iſaiah, there ſhall be no more thence an Infant of dayes, nor an old man that hath filled his dayes: for the Child ſhall dye an hundred yeares old, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> That, if this be expounded by <hi>Iohns Revelation,</hi> it cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of an interpretation ſutable to the ſtate of this world: for he ſaith, there ſhall be no <hi>death</hi> there, <hi>cap.</hi> 21. 4. and before he ſheweth, that <hi>Death (the laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed) was caſt into the Lake:</hi> Therefore, it is impoſſible there ſhould be any <hi>death there.</hi> So that thoſe expreſſions of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> are <hi>metaphoricall,</hi> to expreſſe the durance of their ſtate, which <hi>Iohn</hi> revealeth, to be for <hi>ever and ever, cap.</hi> 22. 5. Some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed attribute this of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to the <hi>Thouſand years of Chriſts Raigne</hi> in the Goſpels glory, which commeth betwixt <hi>the Fall of the Beaſt</hi> and <hi>the wars of Gog and Magog;</hi> to which though it ſhould relate, yet that <hi>double cord</hi> of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> is ſufficient to confirm the thing, both without contradiction plainly and expreſly affirming this <hi>New Creation</hi> to be after the deſtruction of the <hi>old.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:171460:15"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> 
                  <hi>For Chriſt is not entred into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into heaven it ſelfe, now to appeare in the preſence of God for us, Heb.</hi> 9. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> If the ſubject or matter in hand of that place be obſerved, the obſcurity or ſeeming contradiction hereto will vaniſh: the ſubject thereof is, the ſtate of the two <hi>Covenants</hi> or <hi>Testaments;</hi> the <hi>Old</hi> and the <hi>New:</hi> the firſt worldly and carnall, the other heavenly and ſpiritual; the firſt the ſhadow, the ſecond the ſubſtance; the firſt had a <hi>worldly Sanctuary,</hi> a <hi>Tabernacle made, with carnall Ordinances, patterns of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things to come;</hi> which in this very place is called <hi>holy places made with hands, which were figures of the true, into which Chriſt entred not, but into heaven it ſelfe;</hi> that is, <hi>the Holyeſt of all, which was not made manifeſt while the firſt Tabernacle was ſtanding, Ver.</hi> 8. 12. which in this place is expreſſed by the title of <hi>heauen it ſelfe,</hi> not intending the place of glory for the dead Saints, or his locall aſcenſion into any ſuperiour materiall place, but reſpecting his <hi>Mediation</hi> or <hi>Offering of himſelfe,</hi> whereby <hi>now</hi> (and for ever) <hi>to appeare in the preſence of God for us:</hi> as ver. 25. &amp; 26. further evidence.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, by the <hi>third heavens and Paradiſe</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 2. 4. is meant nothing elſe but ſuch a <hi>rapture</hi> as <hi>Daniel, Paul, Iohn,</hi> &amp;c. were in, when the Lord appeared to them in <hi>Viſions,</hi> to declare wonderfull things unto them; for he that was thus <hi>caught up, heard unſpeakable words, which was not lawfull for man to utter; Ver.</hi> 14. And for <hi>Paradiſe</hi> in the other place, <hi>[To day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe]</hi> If it be taken of any condition to be in that preſent day, it muſt be the ſame he was in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; for he was to be <hi>with</hi> him, and that was <hi>at reſt, where the wicked ceaſe from troubling, Iob</hi> 4. 17. <hi>where the priſoners reſt together, and hear not the voice of the oppreſſour, Ver.</hi> 18. If not to reſpect the preſent day, or any condition therein, (as is moſt probable) then it muſt be meant, (as the <hi>Malefactour</hi> deſired) when he was in his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which could not be before his Reſurrection: therefore, the <hi>Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi> could enjoy no ſuch <hi>ſoulary</hi> beatitude, as from hence is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that before he had received this <hi>Kingdome</hi> himſelfe; but muſt receive the <hi>Paradiſe</hi> as Chriſt did, by a totall Reſurrection: wherefore it may well be he was one of the Saints that roſe again ſoone after Chriſts Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 53.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 9.</label> 
                  <hi>By faith Enoch was tranſlated, &amp;c. Heb.</hi> 11. 5. <hi>And Elijah went up by a whirl-wind into heauen,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 11. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This no way helpeth the fancie of the ſoule to a Paradiſe, but rather wholly confounds the conceit; for <hi>Elijah</hi> left his <hi>mantle,</hi> not his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171460:16"/> body behind, when he aſcended the fierie charriot, and <hi>Enoch</hi> was whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken up by God, both tranſlated or changed, and therefore, ſaid, not to ſee death, becauſe they did not <hi>ſleep</hi> in their <hi>change:</hi> for in Scripture we reade of a threefold gradation in death; the one ſleeping in corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is generall, another ſleeping but not ſeeing corruption, as Chriſts, the laſt a ſudden change, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold, I ſhew you a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, we ſhall not all ſleep, but we ſhall all be changed, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, &amp;c.</hi> and ſuch as this, was that of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah;</hi> and this may beare the title of death too, for as the other is a mediate, this is an immediate change, both end, and meet in one period, <hi>mortality ſwallowed up of life.</hi> And whereas before I affirme, that none ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Chriſt aſcended into heaven ſince the Creation, I mean of thoſe that <hi>ſlept,</hi> of whom he was the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 20.</p>
               <p>Now that I may not ſeem to any, to contradict what before I affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning the <hi>New Heauens</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> as if I ſhould make this place into which they aſcended, to be the place intended for the Saints generally at the Reſurrection, and ſo overthrow my former aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, I ſhall ſhew the difference, which if conſidered, will remove the obſcurity: For before, the place intended for the Saints, was cleerly proved <hi>incoruptible,</hi> and <hi>euerlaſting,</hi> whereas the place into which they aſcended, is corruptible, and ſhall paſſe away, and its place no more be found; for the Scripture is plaine, they aſcended into Heaven, and as plaine the Heavens ſhall be conſumed with fire: But may be, it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that Chriſt and the reſt paſſed the limits of the Creation, or that the Heavens, except that where he is, ſhall be diſſolved.</p>
               <p>To wich I Anſwer, that the Scripture makes no ſuch diſtinction or difference, but ſaith, the Heavens ſhall melt away; or import any thing by Heaven in thoſe places which ſpeak even of Chriſts Aſcenſion, then the ſame, or part of the ſame meant by Heavens in other places which ſpeak of the diſſolution.</p>
               <p>Further, Reaſon tels us, that he muſt be within the compaſſe of the Creation, for there is no <hi>beyond,</hi> without it <hi>place</hi> or <hi>being</hi> is impoſſible; Humanity though glorifyed is but a Creature, and why not then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Creation as well as the Angels, creatures as glorious as glorified humanity? <hi>(Luke</hi> 20. 36.) if a Creature, therefore within the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, elſe could it not be a Creature, his glorification alters not his Creatureſhip; and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Heauen muſt contain him till the reſtitution of all things, Act.</hi> 3. 31: and every <hi>Continent</hi> implyeth a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place, and every place muſt be materiall, for <hi>non datur vacuum,</hi> and every matter muſt imply creation, elſe it could not be: therefore he is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171460:16"/> within the Creation. Moreover, his Humanity not being <hi>ubiquitorie,</hi> that is, every where at once, he muſt be in the creation, and in ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place of the creation.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing <hi>Heaven</hi> in Scripture is frequently uſed, to expreſſe height or excellencie of degree or dignity of a thing, (as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 32. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 10.) and he aſcended upward from the Earth into ſome part of the coeleſtiall bodies above, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 10. therefore, without doubt he muſt be in the moſt excellent, glorious, and heavenly part thereof, which is the SUN, the moſt excellent piece of <note place="margin">Chriſts A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cenſion i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the whole Creation, the Epitome of Gods power, conveyour of life, growth, ſtrength, and being to every Creature under Heaven, it may be with other things, but nothing without it, the brightneſſe whereof we are not able to behold at the fartheſt diſtance, and according to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Copernichus</hi> and <hi>Tycho Braheus,</hi> it is higheſt in ſtation to the whole Creation: And it is called by the Learned, <hi>Cor Coeli, Anima &amp; Oculus mundi, Planetarum &amp; Fixarum Choragus, Author generationis:</hi> Fitly therefore may it be called the <hi>Right hand of God,</hi> by which through Chriſt <hi>in him we liue, moue, and haue our being;</hi> for it is that which reflecteth the brightneſſe, glory, and power of the Creatour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Creatures mortall; his glory muſt of neceſſity be the light, elſe light could not be, therefore it muſt be by reflection, elſe would it be too glorious for mortall eyes, we could not ſee it and live: hee hath drawne a veile (the body of the Sun) before our eyes, that we may ſtand in his ſhadow and live; for this light is but his ſhadow, which the Sun as a glaſſe caſteth upon the Creatures, it fills the Moon, Stars, and all Sublunars with as much of his glory as they are able to contain: <hi>Therefore the children of men put their truſt under the ſhadow of his wings: for with him is the fountaine of life, and in his light we ſhall ſee light, Ioh.</hi> 36. 7. 9. yea, ſuch glory is he of, that his ſhadow is our light, we can ſee him but in part, a glimpſe of his glory filleth our eyes, yea the whole world with light, <hi>he is light, and in him is no darkneſſe:</hi> therefore light muſt come from him, or elſe all would be darke, nay were he not, there never could be Hell, or <hi>outer darkneſſe;</hi> for its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commeth by withdrawing both of ſhadow and ſubſtance of his glory, a <hi>great gulfe</hi> ſhall be betwixt it and the place of the Saints, that is, there ſhall be ſuch a condenſe interpoſition, as nothing ſhall be to reflect the brightneſſe of his glory upon it, ſo that it is impoſſible for them to find the light, and for the Saints to fall into the dark. If Gods glory be not light, but true light a created matter, then at the diſſolution true light ſhall be diſſolved for ever, and <hi>no more place found for it:</hi> ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171460:17"/> in the <hi>New Ieruſalem</hi> there ſhall be no light, but the Saints as well as the Divels ſhall be in continuall darkneſſe: for there ſhall be no new light created for it, implyed in theſe words, <hi>it ſhall have no need of the Sun nor Moon, but the glory of God ſhall inlighten it,</hi> (and that which inlightneth muſt needs be light) <hi>and the Lamb is the light thereof;</hi> and he ſhall be the ſame he is now, <hi>yeſterday and to day the ſame for ever, Heb.</hi> 14. 8. Therefore this inlightning glory, or glorious light that he dwelleth in now, ſhall be the light then, diſcovered naked without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, they being enabled to receive it, their corruption having put on incorruption. If God be not true light, the Creation could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire; for if fire be matter created, fire muſt be burnt with fire, but that is impoſſible: therefore, Gods glory or light muſt be this conſuming fire, and not without reaſon, for hold a <hi>Burning-glaſſe</hi> againſt the light of the Sun, and the contracted light meeting with a groſſe body, cauſeth it to burne: the reaſon why any thing burneth, is by the combuſtable groſſenes of the body the which contracted light meeteth with, whereon it feeds, the corruption whereof conſumeth or vaniſheth before the purity of the light; for that which we call by the word, <hi>fire,</hi> is nothing but contradicted light, whoſe nature is not to burne, but the heat and burning commeth from the groſſenes of the matter it meets, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it, that a <hi>Sea-cole</hi> fire is hotter then one of <hi>wood,</hi> the <hi>coale</hi> hotter then the <hi>flame:</hi> So when the true light is diſplayed, or light appeareth naked, that is, when Chriſt appeareth naked, that is, when Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to Judgment, <hi>clothed with honour and majeſty, covered with light as with a garment, Pſal.</hi> 104. 1. 2 (inlightned with the glory of the Deity,) it will be to the Creation a <hi>conſuming fire;</hi> elſe might we behold him and live: but our corruption is not able to ſtand in his light; for no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall we behold it, but we ſhall be changed in the twinkling of an eye: and then ſhall we be enabled, as <hi>Iob</hi> hath it, <hi>in his light to ſee light,</hi> Therefore was it, that the <hi>Lord put Moſes in the clift of a rocke while his glory paſſed by;</hi> becauſe <hi>his face</hi> (or naked glory) was not to be <hi>ſeen,</hi> but his <hi>back parts</hi> (or glory through a vaile) <hi>no man being able to ſee it</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>and live, Exod</hi> 33. 20. 21. 22. 23. If God were not light, there could be neither Sun, Moon, nor Stars to give light, or any light be in the world; yea the world could never have been, or could there be any God, or any thing: for if God be not light, he muſt be darkneſſe: now darkneſſe is no <hi>being,</hi> or can give <hi>being</hi> to any thing, its but a depravation of light: <hi>is not</hi> cannot <hi>be,</hi> or give <hi>being:</hi> Therefore, to ſay God is not <hi>light,</hi> is to ſay, he <hi>is not,</hi> or any Creation ever was or is: ſo that <hi>light</hi> is from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting to everlaſting: As this formed light, or inlightning ſhaddow is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171460:17"/> now the Authour of motion, generation, and ſubſiſtance; ſo in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the ſubſtance or <hi>true light</hi> was the beginner, and by it all <hi>beings</hi> had their beginnings: Wherefore, God being true light, it followeth, true light is no creature, or could be created, except God did create him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And further, that he is light, the miraculous diſcovery of himſelf in viſions by <hi>light</hi> doth evidence: as, his appearance to <hi>Moſes</hi> in a <hi>flame of fire, Exod.</hi> 3. 2. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10. 4. his <hi>filling the Court with the brightneſſe of his glory,</hi> his appearance to <hi>Peter</hi> in a <hi>light,</hi> which <hi>ſhined in the priſon, Act.</hi> 12. 7. and to <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>a great light, which ſhone round about him.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>day after day, and night after night</hi> declare that he is <hi>light,</hi> for what is <hi>outer darkneſſe</hi> but deprivation of his <hi>preſence?</hi> ſo the abſence of the Sun light manifeſts it a deprivation in ſome meaſure of his <hi>preſence,</hi> the ſhaddow of his glory, or reflected light; becauſe then is the fitteſt time for conjuration or dealing with Divels, <hi>raiſing of ſpirits,</hi> or the like, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Cornelius Agrippa;</hi> their power being greateſt at the fartheſt diſtance of his glory, <hi>Diabolicall apparitions,</hi> or <hi>Walkes</hi> of Devils in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, are then only frequent, and the greater this deprivation is, the more formidable, uncough, and terrible it is, as a dayly ſhaddow, or type of eternall night, or <hi>outer darknes.</hi> And when Chriſt both God and Man was in the depth of his paſſion, the Sun was darkened, that he cried out, <hi>my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> as if his preſence in that <hi>Eclipſe</hi> had quite left him: which plainly implyes, that <hi>God is light,</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe</hi> the abſence of his glory, the which the more it is, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> 
                  <hi>God ſaid, let there be light, and there was light:</hi> Ergo, light was created.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> If that place be compared to what is aſcribed to the fourth dayes work, and it will be found no other, as the body of the Sun, which was to caſt the ſhadow of his brightneſſe for light upon the earth, and ſo time diſtinguiſhed into day and night by its preſence and abſence: in which ſence light may be ſaid to be made, and ſo ſhall have an end, this ſhadow or his <hi>back parts</hi> we behold, but not the ſubſtance, <hi>his face,</hi> or true light, which by mortality cannot be <hi>ſeen, Exod.</hi> 33. 20. that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. Now ſeeing it is cleare, that God is the true light which light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the world, and every one that commeth therein, and this glory chiefly in the Sun, the Moderatour and upholder of the whole Creation. Therefore, there muſt Chriſt be, or elſe he fitteth not at the <hi>right hand of God</hi> in all things, <hi>or hath immortallity dwelling in light, the which no man can approach.</hi> As for the <hi>Coelum Empyreum</hi> which the <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> have invented for his reſidence, I know no better ground they have for it, then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171460:18"/> ſuch as <hi>Dromodotus</hi> the Philoſopher in <hi>Pedantius</hi> had to prove there was Divels: <hi>Sunt Antipodes:</hi> Ergo <hi>Daemones. Sunt Coeli:</hi> Ergo <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Empyreum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 10.</label> 
                  <hi>Then ſhall the duſt returne to the earth, as it was, and the ſpirit ſhall returne to God who gave it. Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> By ſpirit cannot be meant ſuch a thing as the ſoul, except all ſoules go to God, and none to the Devil: for it is indifferently ſpoken of all: but by <hi>ſpirit</hi> is meant life, which hath various expreſſions in Scripture: it is the will of God, that duſt ſhalbe made man, and live, and it is done, and he liveth; and his will that it ſhall dye, and it dyeth, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth to what it was: he withdraweth his communicated power, and man ceaſeth, <hi>[the ſpirit ſhall returne]</hi> the communication, power, or faculty of life ſhall ceaſe, <hi>[to God that gave it]</hi> in him that communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, or gave it, <hi>in whom we live, move and have our being:</hi> no otherwiſe mans <hi>ſpirit</hi> (or life) <hi>returneth to God that gave it: he taketh away the breath and the creatures dye, and returne to their duſt, Pſal.</hi> 104. 29. for the <hi>life</hi> of man <hi>is even a vapour that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away. Iam.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 11.</label> 
                  <hi>And they ſtoned Steven, calling upon God, and ſaying, Lord Ieſus receive my ſpirit. Act.</hi> 7. 59.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This is a commendation of his life or being into the hands of God, <hi>in whom with Chriſt our lives are hid, Col.</hi> 3. 3. as a full aſſurance of his hope and faith in the Reſurrection, <hi>that when Chriſt who is our life, ſhould appeare, he alſo might appeare with him in glory: For God is not the God of the dead, but of the living: for all live unto him, Luke.</hi> 20. 38. And thus, and no otherwiſe, was his <hi>ſpirit commended, or returned to him that gave it, whoſe ſpirit goeth forth, and we are renewed, Pſal.</hi> 104. 30. anſwerable to that of the <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> into whom <hi>the ſpirit of life from God,</hi> after they had <hi>lien dead three dayes and an halfe, entered into them, and they ſtood upon their feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 12.</label> 
                  <hi>God breathed into his noſtrils the breath of life. Gen.</hi> 2. 7. Ergo man hath an immortall ſoul.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Then ſo is the foul of a Beaſt; for <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>their breath is all one Eccl.</hi> 3. 19. and <hi>David</hi> reckoning up the creatures, and man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, ſaith indifferently of them all, God <hi>hideth</hi> his <hi>face, and they are troubled,</hi> he <hi>taketh away their breath, they dye, and returne to their duſt, Pſal.</hi> 104. 29. and this is further amplified in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 33. <hi>to every thing in the Earth wherein there is a living ſoul &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 7. 21. 22. <hi>all fleſh dyed, in whoſe noſtrils was the breath of life:</hi> and <hi>Num.</hi> 31. 28. all which make no difference betwixt them, <hi>but as the one dyeth, ſo dyeth the</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171460:18"/> 
                  <hi>other, and man hath no preheminence above a beaſt: For what man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death, or deliver his ſoul from the hand of the grave? Selah. Pſal.</hi> 89. 48.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object. 13.</label> 
                  <hi>And it came to paſſe the Beggar dyed, and was carried by Angels into Abrahams boſome &amp;c. Luke</hi> 16. from the 22. to the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> There was never ſuch a man as <hi>Dives</hi> or <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or ever ſuch a thing happened, no more then <hi>Iothams</hi> Trees did <hi>walke</hi> and <hi>talke. Iud.</hi> 9. 8. but was a Parable, to prove, that nothing is more effectuall for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion then the ordinary preaching of the Word by the miniſtration of the ſervants of God: Further, the conſequence concerning the ſoul is but drawn from the literall ſence, in which ſence I ſhall deny it canonicall Scripture; for it makes in that ſence more for bodies then the ſouls pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent being in Heaven or Hell, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. 24. and maketh <hi>Abraham</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Damned, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. 25. 27. 30. and <hi>ver.</hi> 22. <hi>Dives dyed and was buried;</hi> and yet <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>he lift up his eyes being in torment, and ſeeth Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 25. he cryed for <hi>Lazarus to dip the tip of his finger to coole his tongue;</hi> which in the literall ſence thus applycated, muſt needs be contradictory, unleſſe his <hi>eyes, tongue,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus finger</hi> was not buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or their ſouls had corporeall corpulent members, which to conceit is ridiculous: Therefore, from this place the Reſurrection of the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of Judgment (even as ſoon as a man is buried) may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be proved, then ſuch a preſent <hi>ſoularie</hi> enterance into Heaven or Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 14.</label> 
                  <hi>By which alſo he went, and preached to them in priſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> 
                  <hi>[By which]</hi> that is, by that whereby he was <hi>quickened,</hi> or rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead; his divine nature, the God-head; as the foregoing words (whereon the ſence of thoſe depend) doth evidence, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Chriſt once ſuffered &amp;c. death in the fleſh, but quickened by the ſpirit,</hi> (ver. 19.) <hi>by which alſo he went &amp;c.</hi> So that he went and preached by <hi>that,</hi> whereby he was quickened or raiſed: Therefore, the preaching, here meant, was not by that which was raiſed: but by that which did raiſe; which was miniſterially, as the following words further evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſhewing to whom he preached, <hi>even thoſe which were diſobedient in the dayes of Noah, on whom the long ſuffering of God waited while the Arke was a preparing:</hi> thoſe were the <hi>ſpirits</hi> here meant, the wicked of thoſe dayes, which are now in <hi>priſon,</hi> that is, dead or impriſoned in the Elements. Here the grave or death is called a <hi>priſon,</hi> as indeed it is, for therein all that dye are reſerved in the chaines of death (the Elements) not to be delivered till Judgement, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 13. according to <hi>Iob.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>there the priſoners reſt together.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:171460:19"/>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 15.</label> 
                  <hi>Therefore gloryfie God in your body, and in your ſpirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Before, he calleth the body <hi>the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, ver.</hi> 29. and <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>the members of Chriſt;</hi> which needs muſt be the whole man, and not his bare carcaſe, for <hi>in death who can praiſe the Lord?</hi> in it can be no habitation for the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> and therein were they to <hi>glorifie</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Abſurd.</note> 
                  <hi>God:</hi> to make <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>head</hi> of ſuch <hi>members,</hi> were to make God, <hi>the God of the dead and not of the living:</hi> therefore, by <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> is meant whole man, aiming at a thorough and perfect <hi>ſanctification,</hi> as well in that which reſpecteth thought, <hi>[the ſpirit]</hi> as in that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth action, <hi>[the body:]</hi> inwardly to glorifie God, as well as out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly <hi>to flee fornication, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 16.</label> 
                  <hi>I ſaw under the Altar the ſoules of them that were ſlaine for the word of God, &amp;c. and they cried with a loud voyce, &amp;c. Revel.</hi> 6. 10. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> They were ſuch <hi>ſouls as lay under the Altar flaine,</hi> or ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or as <hi>ver.</hi> 11. hath it, <hi>were killed;</hi> theſe therefore being <hi>dead ſoules,</hi> or martyred Saints, their <hi>cry</hi> muſt be as the <hi>cry of the blood of Abel:</hi> And the like <hi>viſion</hi> of dead Saints confirmes it, as <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 4. 5. <hi>And I ſaw the ſoules of them that were beheaded for the witneſſe of Ieſus, and they lived, and raigned with Chriſt a thouſand yeares: but the reſt of the dead lived not again till &amp;c.</hi> whence it is plaine, that he beheld the Reſurrection, or reſtoration of life unto <hi>dead ſoules,</hi> even <hi>of them that were beheaded,</hi> but the <hi>reſt</hi> lay dead, or <hi>lived not again till &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much of illegitimate <hi>Objections</hi> from Scripture: Now to the probation hereof from <hi>Procreation</hi> or <hi>Generation,</hi> and as near as I can to reſolve all occurrent <hi>Objections</hi> thereon, that ſhall confront.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of procreation, how from thence this Mortallity is proved.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is ſuppoſed (as I conceive) by none, that what naturally proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from Man ſimply by the courſe of nature, can be immortall, but muſt firſt taſt of mortality: And therefore there are two ſorts of <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to maintaine this Heatheniſh Invention about the ſoul, whereon its immortality is grounded, which I ſhall chiefly encounter: the one, that it is created, and infuſed at the conception, and ſo only Gods work. The other, that it is concepted by the woman through the concurrence of the ſeed of both ſexes, but not ſimply by the courſe of nature, but by the ſupernaturall and extraordinary aſſiſtance or efficacy of God in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171460:19"/> more then in other creatures: and ſo partly mans, and partly Gods work. But that I may utterly demoliſh the ſtructure of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, I ſhall turne up the foundation of each kind in its place: But firſt I ſhall ſpeak a word or two in generall of <hi>Procreation</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p>That whole man is generated by man, obſerve: That as the whole Tree is potentially in the ſeed, and actually in time ſpringeth from it: or as many graines of wheat are in one graine virtually, and perfectly actuall in time: ſo in the ſeed of mankind, is whole man potentially, and wholly actuall in time; or all <hi>Adams</hi> ſucceſſion, which in time are propagated, were wholly in him, life and limbs, or as it is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſoule and body. So that whatſoever in time is actuall by procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it was at firſt potentially wholly in its originall.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>Generatum ſequitur naturam generantis (He begat a ſonne in his owne image, Gen.</hi> 5. 3.) is not onely philoſophically, but Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gically true, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 16. <hi>Iob</hi> 4. 14. Therefore, mortall <hi>Adam</hi> muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get mortall children in his owne likeneſſe, ſoule and body, except the ſoule was no part of his likeneſſe: For that which is immortall can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not generatively proceed from that which is mortall, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that which is borne of the fleſh is</hi> (as it ſelfe is, corruptible, mutable) <hi>fleſh, Iohn</hi> 3. 6. ſo then by this mortall fleſh, cannot be generated an immortall ſpirit, or ſoule that can ſubſiſt by it ſelfe diſſolved from the fleſh; for if it ſhould, in <note n="h" place="margin">32. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> that act it ſhould goe beyond it ſelfe, which is impoſſible; and thereby more ſhould be done <note n="i" place="margin">33. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> by man and woman in generation, then God did or could doe in the Creation; for he neither did, or could create any thing greater, purer, or more excellent of nature then himſelfe, and ſuch as could ſubſiſt without him: But if this doctrine be true, (as <hi>Woolner</hi> in his <hi>Originall of the ſoul</hi> averreth) fleſhly man by a fleſhly generation, or mixture of the ſeed of both Sexes doth beget or conceive ſomething greater, purer, and more excellent then himſelfe, an immortall ſubſtance, an Angelicall entitie, <hi>the Soule,</hi> that can ſubſiſt without the fleſh by which it is; which is as fire <note n="k" place="margin">34. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> without light, earth without heavineſſe, groſneſſe, &amp;c. ſhould be, by which they are: and further, the <hi>Effect</hi> to be <hi>prior dignitate,</hi> precedent to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as if a man <note n="l" place="margin">35. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe a creature, ſhould be before his Creator: But if it be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that the ſoule is generated by the ſoule, as the body by the body. I Anſwer, then there muſt be <note n="m" place="margin">36. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He</hi> ſoules and <hi>She</hi> ſoules: for without Sexes is no generation.</p>
               <p>But now to the firſt ſort, who ſay it is by infuſion, or as the ſaying is, <hi>Creando infunditur, &amp; infundendo creatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:171460:20"/>
               <p> To which I Anſwer, that in conception there is corruption or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, according to the proverb, <hi>corruptio unius eſt generatio alterius:</hi> ſo that if it be by conceiving or creating infuſed, and by infuſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted or created, that is as much to ſay, it is <note n="n" place="margin">37 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> made in the marring, and mard in the making: or, infuſed in the marring, and mard in the infuſion: whence followeth, that it is neither conceived, created, nor infuſed; neither made, nor mard: but muſt be, if it be, no man knowes what, or how; <note n="o" place="margin">38 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> whether an Angel, a Beaſt, or a Monſter, any thing, or nothing: Riddle me, riddle me what's this? a Soule, a Soule! <hi>Creando infunditur, &amp; infundendo creatur!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if the Soule be a creature infuſed, then Chriſt did not take the whole manhood from the ſeed of the woman, but worſe then a bare <note place="margin">p 39 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> brutiſh body, a dead carcaſe: But Chriſt was made of the ſeed of the woman according to the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 30. and was as we are, ſinne excepted, <hi>Heb.</hi> 14. 15. and this our Image he received wholly from the woman: Therefore receiving his whole humanitie from her, the ſoule can be no infuſed creature.</p>
               <p>3. That which brake the Serpents head was Chriſts humanity: But the ſeed of the woman brake the Serpents head: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. If we conſiſt of ſoule and body, and are not men without both, and receive not our ſoules from him, but are daily created: Then <hi>Adam</hi> 
                  <note n="q" place="margin">40 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> is the father of no man. 2. Chriſt cannot be the <note n="r" place="margin">41 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Son of man,</hi> and ſo no Saviour, becauſe thereby his manhood, conſtitutive part, even that which ſhould make him man, could not be by the ſeed of the woman. 4. So a man <note n="ſ" place="margin">42 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> is as much a father of <hi>fleas</hi> and <hi>lice,</hi> which receive their matter from him, as of his children. 5. Whereas God bleſſed man, and bid him, as the reſt of the creatures in their kind, fill the Earth in his kind with men: then he commanded him <note n="t" place="margin">43 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> to doe more then he had given him power for: And ſo to content nature, end ſupply her imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility to obey, is forced to a daily creation. 6. Then God finiſhed not the Creation in <note n="*" place="margin">Abſurd.</note> ſixe dayes, but reſted before hee had done crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, If the ſoule be infuſed, it muſt be at the conception, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the conception: If at the conception, then every <note n="v" place="margin">45 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> abortive concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath an immortall ſpirit in it, and muſt riſe againe: If after, then there is growth before <note n="w" place="margin">46 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> there is life, which is impoſſible; for the ſoule is made the vegetive as well as the motive, ſenſitive or rationall part: and if this immortall ſpirit be ſomething elſe, then we are not conceived <note n="x" place="margin">47 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> perfect men, and as we are conceived, ſo are we borne, <note n="y" place="margin">48 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>trees, brutes,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:171460:20"/> or I know not what, and afterwards are made men, if we be men at all: and ſo <note n="z" place="margin">49 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> Infants that dye in the wombe, or in the birth are little better then trees, and worſe then beaſts.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, if the ſoule be not generated with the body, but a creature infuſed into a dead body, for they ſay, the ſoule is <hi>forma formans,</hi> that giveth life, and motion to the body: Then it is lawfull to be a <note n="*" place="margin">Abſurd.</note> 
                  <hi>Nigro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer:</hi> for <hi>Nigromancie</hi> is nothing but putting a ſpirit into a dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſo it is but an imitation of God, and God the onely <hi>Nigroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> and <note n="a" place="margin">50. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> all the men in the world but <hi>Nigromantick Apparitions,</hi> whoſe ſpirits when they have done the work for which they were put into the bodies, deſert them, as other conjured Ghoſts doe.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, It is granted that the body conſidered meerly ſenſitive cannot ſinne, and that the body is but an inſtrument, or as the pen in the hand of a Writer, to the Soule, whereby it acts and moves: Therefore, if the Soule come immediately from God, or there be an immediate work of his in its production; then of neceſſity, that immortall thing, and not our mortall fleſh, is Author of all ſinne, and it onely prone to all ſinne, and not the fleſh, no more then a conduite though a meet inſtrument to convey water is the author; or fount of water, or prone to ſpring: And ſo Gods immediate hand <note n="b" place="margin">51. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> is the cauſe of all ſin, that man had better been without this ſoul; for it muſt needs be ſome damnable wicked ſpirit, <note n="c" place="margin">52. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> or ſome Devil that God puts in him; for ſuch as the fruit is, ſuch muſt the tree be: but the fruit is damnably wicked: Therefore, the Soul muſt be ſome damnable wicked thing: No marvell then if Reprobates muſt needs ſin and be damned, ſince God <hi>infuſes</hi> ſuch a <hi>malignant Soul,</hi> that councels them with <hi>Iobs</hi> wife to <hi>curſe God and dye,</hi> yea ſuch a one as wholy works out their condemnation: This is as if a man ſhould <note n="d" place="margin">53. <hi>Abſ</hi>
                  </note> break his horſes legs and then knocke out his brains for halting. If it be ſaid the ſoul comes pure from God, and it is the body that corrupteth it. I Anſwer, that this to excuſe God one way, makes him like the tyrant <hi>Mezentius,</hi> that bound living men to dead bodyes, till the putrefaction <note place="margin">Vir. Aen. <hi>Abſurd.</hi>
                  </note> and corruption of the ſtinking corps had killed them. Beſides, the mind may ſin without the Action of the body, but not the body without the mind, for a man may covet in his mind, and not act with his body, and yet ſin; but if he do with his body, and not conſent with his mind, he ſinneth not: as for example, a man may accidentally and ignorantly kill a man by a blow, which was never intended or aimed at him, and yet he not guilty of murther: but if he intend it in his mind, though he never do it, he is guilty: Therefore the body may be made ſinfull by the ſoul, but not the ſoul by the body.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171460:21"/>
               <p> Now to the other kind, who ſay, that this ſupernaturall work by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is effected by Gods ſpeciall ſupernaturall aſſiſtance, operating or applicated to this naturall aptitude, in whoſe mutuall concurrence this immortall ſubſtance is concepted, and in conception united to the fleſh, the whole in the whole, and the whole in every part.</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, that there is no more ſpeciall ſupernaturall effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency from God in mans procreation then in other creatures, but that ſpeciall gift or naturall inſtinct to every kind of creature given in the Creation to produce its kind, whether vegetative, ſenſitive, or rationall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 38. for the gift or bleſſing is all one and the ſame, and alike unto all according to their kinds, as appears, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 22. God bleſſed the <hi>Fowles</hi> and <hi>Fiſh,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Be fruitfull and multiply, and fill the waters in the Seas, and let the Fowles multiply in the earth:</hi> And verſe 28. the ſelfe ſame he ſpeaks of man and woman, <hi>And God bleſſed them, and ſaid unto them, Be fruitfull, and repleniſh the earth:</hi> and by this bleſſing, or Natures generall inſtinct equally unto all, men and all other creatures continue their multiplications and procreations: So that the <hi>Fowles, Fiſh,</hi> &amp;c. have as great and ſpeciall aſſiſtance as Man in their conceptions and procreations, equally mediate and naturall: Therefore, if by Mans conception an Angelicall immortall Soul is producted, ſo likewiſe is there the <note n="e" place="margin">54. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> like in other creatures. The reſult of all which is this, that as Fiſh, Birds, and Beaſts each in their kind procreate their kind without any tranſcendency of nature: So man in his kind begets man, corruptible man begets nothing but what is corruptible, not halfe mortall, halfe immortall, halfe Angel, halfe man; but compleat man totally mortall: for through mortall organs immortality cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, or therein poſſibly reſide.</p>
               <p>If it be ſcrupled, that this deſtroyeth the hope of our faith. I Anſwer, It doth but remove it from a falſe principle to a true, from a deceitfull fancie to an infallible object, the Reſurrection: For though I aſcribe nothing actually to nature, but corruption; yet potentially I aſcribe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption: as to the kernill of an Apple a Tree may not actually, yet potentially be aſcribed: So I grant, that Nature produceth the <hi>Seed,</hi> to which when ſhe hath done her elementary work, even all that ſhee can doe, and in all things tranſient finiſhed her courſe, even from that corrupted ſeed Chriſt ſupernaturally raiſeth an incortuptible body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 36. <hi>Thou foole, that which thou ſoweſt is not quickned, except it die; it is ſowne in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption; it is ſowne a naturall body, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body:</hi> Therefore nothing of Man can be immortall, but what firſt hath ſeen corruption. So that, if that which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171460:21"/> is made the better and moſt excellent part of Man, without which he is NO MAN (as is held) titled the <hi>Soul,</hi> ſhall not ſee corruption, it ſhall not <note n="f" place="margin">55. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> participate of the immortallity purchaſed by Chriſt, but muſt needs periſh except there be <hi>Ens extra Deum,</hi> as that ſtrange invented <hi>Entitie</hi> muſt needs be, and ſo conſequently, <note n="g" place="margin">56. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> NO MAN ſhall be ſaved: And as before it incur'd this Abſurdity, that the <hi>Soules</hi> of the damned ſhall not periſh, but ſtand as well as the <hi>Stative Angels:</hi> So by this, the <hi>Soules</hi> both of the <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall for ever ceaſe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be immortallized at the <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> And thence the denyall both of <hi>Reſurrection, Condemnation,</hi> and <hi>Salvation, Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell, God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">57. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> is inavoydable: After ruſheth in the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Blaſphemy, <note n="i" place="margin">58. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Let us eat, and drinke, for to morrow we die:</hi> And ſo, <note n="k" place="margin">59. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſo many bellyes, ſo many Gods, and no other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is objected, <hi>That the rareneſſe of conception argues a ſupernaturall immediate aſſiſtance eſſentiall, without which the ſoul cannot be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> That commeth by a naturall defect, and not by the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of Gods immediate hand, elſe he ſhould have a ſpeciall and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand in Adultery: And ſo Whoremongers and Adulterers ſets God a work to create <hi>Souls</hi> for <note n="k" place="margin">61. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> their <hi>Baſtards,</hi> which is to make God a ſlave to their luſts.</p>
               <p>Further, it is objected, <hi>That God hath from eternity decreed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man above all creatures, both who ſhould come into the world, and at what time: Therefore, accordingly he muſt have a work in mans concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on above other creatures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> No ſuch thing followeth, for <hi>time</hi> and <hi>number</hi> may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, and yet the due courſe of nature proceed, as well without as with an immediate aſſiſtance, towards man in his kind, as in Beaſts in their kind.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>Woolner</hi> in his Treatiſe on the <hi>Soul pag.</hi> 115. ſaith, <hi>That the more ſpirituall parts, and chiefly the Soul is</hi> (but partly mediately, partly immediately) <hi>conceived at the firſt inſtant, or union of the ſeed of both Sexes: For by it</hi> (pag. 127. he ſaith,) <hi>the corporeall parts are prepared and perfected:</hi> Therefore, it muſt of neceſſity be at the <hi>firſt inſtant, or elſe no conception:</hi> And pag. 129. <hi>That all Soules, as well of Beaſts, as of men are eſſentially as perfect at the firſt inſtant of conception as ever afterwards,</hi> And pag. 97. he ſaith, <hi>The Soul can live without the body, and cannot be corrupted by it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> That then it followeth, If a woman miſcarry immediately after that very inſtant, <note n="l" place="margin">35. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> that the Soul of that <hi>Effluction</hi> or unſhapen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed peece of <hi>congealed blood</hi> being immortal, muſt needs continue its
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171460:22"/> immortality, and that <hi>Effluction</hi> as well as perfect bodies, ſhall be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againe; for if degrees of corporall perfection hinder, then thoſe that are borne imperfect, as without legs, arms, or hands, or any other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as divers are, they <note n="m" place="margin">63 <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall never be raiſed againe, and ſo out of the compaſſe of Chriſts death: and though it ſhould be granted, that Chriſts death is denyed an <hi>Embrio,</hi> yet that ſoules immortality cannot be nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, for immortality once begun, muſt never have an end, and he ſaith, <hi>it cannot ſuffer with the fleſh:</hi> therefore, if not with the whole maſſe of mans corpulency growne to its full perfection, much leſſe with an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio,</hi> that is ten times leſſe imperfect and invalid; for he ſaith, <hi>it is as perfect at the firſt inſtant as ever afterwards:</hi> therefore, it muſt be ſaved or damned (if there be any for others) but no man knowes how or <note place="margin">Abſurd.</note> which way, except it can be proved, Chriſt dyed for bare ſoules, ſoules without bodies, which will puzzle the cunningeſt ſoule that ever was made in the marring, and mard in the making.</p>
               <p>Further it is objected, <hi>Creatures propagated out of kind, as by bugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; as, Apes, Satyres, &amp;c. are ſuppoſed, are not endowed with reaſonable ſoules:</hi> Ergo, <hi>ſoules are created immediately, or however of neceſſity, Gods ſuperficient power is joyned to the propagation thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> As I will not altogether confidently affirme they have <hi>ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſoules,</hi> ſo will I not altogether deny it: For in Man it is ſome <hi>orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> deficiency more or leſſe, that is the cauſe, that ſome men are leſſe <hi>rationall</hi> then others; for ſome have abundance of wiſdome, and ſome are meere fooles: and in children, whoſe <hi>Organs</hi> are not come to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, there is not ſo much as there is in an <hi>Ape:</hi> This premiſed, why in ſome meaſure as far as by thoſe improper <hi>Organs</hi> can be expreſſed, may they not be <hi>rationall,</hi> though not in the ſame degree as is capable of God, as well as Infants who are as uncapable <hi>pro tempore</hi> as <hi>Apes?</hi> But perchance, it will be replyed, that then <hi>Chriſt dyed for Apes, as well as for Infants.</hi> I Anſwer, Chriſt dyed not for the rationall part ſeparated from the materiall, nor the materiall from the rationall, if there ſhould be ſuch <hi>buggery births,</hi> or if by that unnaturall courſe they ſhould meet in one, (which is impoſſible, for the bleſſing of procreating any thing in its kind, is to the kind) for that neither, but for the naturall produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by the conjunction of both Sexes legitimate from <hi>Adam,</hi> and not ſuch unnaturall by-blowes: As for births out of kind, they come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of the <hi>Curſe,</hi> and cannot any wayes claim priviledge in the <hi>Reſtoration,</hi> but muſt expect with <hi>Thornes, Bryars,</hi> and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Vermin,</hi> and <hi>Filth</hi> which breedeth on corruption, to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, when <hi>mortality is ſwallowed up of life.</hi> For all other <hi>Creatures</hi> as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171460:22"/> well as Man ſhall be raiſed and delivered from death at the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: my Reaſons and grounds for it be theſe. Firſt, that otherwiſe the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Beaſts</hi> &amp;c.</note> curſe in <hi>Adam</hi> would extend further then the bleſſing in Chriſt, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Scriptures: <hi>For as in Adam all dye, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 22. <hi>For the wages of ſinne is death, but the gift of God is eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Rom.</hi> 23. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Death</hi> comming upon all the Creatures by the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> no death being before ſinne, life ſhall come upon all by <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Secondly, the beaſts were not given Man to eate in the <hi>Innocencie,</hi> but to all fleſh wherein was <hi>the breath of life, was given the greene herbe for meat:</hi> Therefore, the death of the beaſts, &amp;c. was part of the <hi>Curſe,</hi> and ſo to be done away by Chriſt. Thirdly, if the other Creatures doe not riſe againe, then Chriſt ſhall not <hi>conquer Death,</hi> but when it is ſaid, <hi>O Death where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy victory?</hi> it will be anſwered in Beaſts, becauſe they are ſtill captivated under its bondage: But <hi>as by one man death entered into the world, Ro.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>and by man came death, by man ſhal come reſurrection from death, and the laſt Enemy that ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is death, and</hi> death <hi>ſhall be ſwallowed up in victory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21. 54. Therefore death ſhall not retaine them, but they muſt be delivered out of its Jawes. Fourthly, thoſe enſuing Scriptures doe clearly prove it: <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 15. to the 23. <hi>All things were created by him and for him, whether they be things in Earth, or things in Heaven: and be not removed away from the hope of the Goſpel, which ye have heard, and which was preached to every creature under heaven:</hi> And Mar. 16. 15. <hi>Go ye into all the world, &amp; preach the Goſpel to every creature:</hi> that is, <hi>Glad tydings,</hi> life and Reſurrection from the bondage of corruption to every Creature by Chriſt: therefore, is he ſaid to be the <hi>Firſt borne of every Creature,</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> that's <hi>borne,</hi> or raiſed <hi>from the Dead:</hi> ſo that thoſe whereof he is the Firſt, muſt follow, that is every creature, elſe could he not be the <hi>Firſt borne from the Dead</hi> of them all. And <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 5. after the diſſolution of all things he ſaith, <hi>Behold, I make all things New:</hi> And <hi>Pſa.</hi> 104. <hi>David</hi> reckoning up <hi>Men, Cattel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> &amp;c. ſaith, <hi>thou takeſt away their breath, and they dye, thou ſendeſt forth thy ſpirit, and reneweſt the face of the earth:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Heavens,</hi> ſaith, <hi>as a veſture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed:</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> ſaith, in the <hi>New earth the Wolf and the Lamb ſhall feed together, and the Lion ſhall eat ſtraw like a Bullock:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 19. 20. 21. <hi>The expectation of the creature waiteth for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the ſons of God: for the creature was made ſubject to vanity, not willingly, but by reaſon of him who hath ſubjected the ſame in hope: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Creature it ſelfe alſo ſhall be delivered from the bondage of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:171460:23"/> 
                  <hi>into the glorious liberty of the children of God: for we know that the whole Creation groaneth, and traveleth in paine till now.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Goſpel</hi> or <hi>Glad Tydings</hi> is unto all, all are under hope, and all things, <hi>men, beaſts, &amp;c.</hi> ſhall be made new, or reſtored at the Reſurrection, and ſo <hi>Death ſhall be ſwallowed up in victory,</hi> and <hi>mortallity of life,</hi> or <hi>Death having given up her dead, ſhall be caſt into the Lake, Rev.</hi> 20. 13. 15. Thus much by the <hi>by:</hi> Now to our matter in hand.</p>
               <p>But be it granted, that thoſe births are not endowed with <hi>reaſonable ſoules,</hi> yet doth it not follow, that <hi>God createth immediately the ſoule, or immediately aſſiſteth nature in its production more then the body:</hi> for this is an inſtance out of kind, therefore cannot expect the bleſſing of the kind, but be as it ſelfe is, <hi>unnaturall and curſed:</hi> for to the kind is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Sexes of the kind, and thereto God hath given the bleſſing to beget its kind, as well for man to beget perfect man, as for the beaſts to beget perfect beaſts; ſo that whatſoever is borne of man naturally, is man, though one be ennobled with more excellencies then another. A <hi>borne Foole</hi> would have been a better inſtance; for if to them <hi>rationall Soules</hi> were denyed, it might be thought, Nature naturally begetteth meere irrationall, brutiſh, inhumane bodies, and rationality, or humanity is a meer ſupernaturall work. To prevent ſuch a cavill, I Anſwer, that by the <hi>Soularies</hi> ground there can be no <note n="n" place="margin">64. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>borne fooles,</hi> Infants new borne, yea an <hi>Embrio</hi> ſhould be as actually <hi>rationall</hi> as men of ripeneſſe of yeares; for they ſay, the <hi>ſoul</hi> is rationality it ſelf, and that rationality is no more of the body, then inke is from the pen, and the ſoul is abſolutely perfect at the firſt inſtant, yea it is <hi>forma formans:</hi> therefore, <hi>naturam expellas, furca licet uſque recurres;</hi> it is made action, which cannot but appeare, for all action is apparant, and they ſay it is an immortall ſpirit, therefore cannot ceaſe, and if not ceaſe, it muſt ſhew it ſelf: Now why are not Infants then as rationall as others? nay, let me ask one <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> If this endleſſe ſoul be <hi>forma formans,</hi> the maker of our bodys, why have we not <note n="o" place="margin">65. <hi>Abſ.</hi>
                  </note> endleſſe bodyes? for <hi>omne tale generat tale,</hi> every like brings forth its like; ſo then, if one be immortall the other muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall. Secondly, I Anſwer, that though ſome are fooles from their birth, yet it doth not follow, that Gods immediate hand is required to mans procreation, but rather the contrary: for imperfections in a thing argue the mediate generation thereof; becauſe no imperfection of any kind can come immediately from the hand of God: imperfections are accidentall, or from the curſe: therefore not of creation, but of procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing all this while we have had to do with this immortall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171460:23"/> Soul, we cannot find, or the <hi>Soularies</hi> tell what it is, ſuch likewiſe is its reſidence; for if we ask where it it? they <hi>flap us i'th mouth</hi> with a <hi>Ridle, tota in toto, &amp; tota in qualibet parte,</hi> the whole in the whole, and the whole in every part: that is, the whole immortall Soul in the whole body, and the whole Soul wholy in every part of the body. To which I <note place="margin">Abſurd</note> Anſwer, that this extends immortality or impoſſibility of death to the body: for if immortality be in every part, then no part of man from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot can be excepted; ſo <hi>we are all</hi> 
                  <note n="p" place="margin">66 <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Soul all over, and every part a whole Soul immortall:</hi> So that it muſt either be held to <note n="q" place="margin">67 <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> be <hi>ubiquitory,</hi> which is an <hi>Attribute</hi> peculiar to God; or elſe multiplicable by a corpulent diviſion: and ſo, were a man min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into <hi>Atomes,</hi> cut into innumerable bits, there would be ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable <note place="margin">r 68 <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> whole Souls, elſe could it not be wholy in every part. <note place="margin">ſ 69 <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſtrum horrendum, ingens; cui quot ſunt corpore</hi> crines,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tot vigiles</hi> Animae <hi>ſupter, mirabile dictu!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus the <hi>Ridle</hi> is unfolded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Teſtimonies of Scripture to prove that whole man is generated, and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat this is true <hi>ſecundum actum naturae,</hi> obſerve the ſence of thoſe enſewing Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ures: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 17. 18. compared with the 22. <hi>ver.</hi> where man and beaſt have an equall bleſſing and charge to propagate their like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. 19. <hi>There is no diſtinction betwixt them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gen. 17. 7. <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed after thee.</hi> Here by <hi>ſeed</hi> muſt be meant perſons and not bare carcaſſes: elſe he had been <hi>the God of dead clots, and not of living ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 46. 26. <hi>All the ſouls that came with Iacob into Egypt which came out of his loynes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Job. 31. 15. <hi>Did not he that made me in the wombe make him? and did not one faſhion us in the wombe?</hi> Ergo, if his ſoul were immediately cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, ſo was his body; for he, that is, his <hi>Entite,</hi> perſon, even all that went to make him man was formed and ſhapen in the womb, both Epithites for procreation and not for creation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 20. 10. 11. 22. <hi>Haſt thou not poured me out as milke, and curdled me like cheeſe? thou haſt clothed me with skin and fleſh, and haſt fenced me with bones and ſinnues, thou haſt granted me life and favour, and thy viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hath preſerved my ſpirit.</hi> Here <hi>Iob</hi> ſets forth exactly the manner
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171460:24"/> of mans procreation, from the act of generation even to his breathing: Firſt, <hi>poured out as milke,</hi> that is, the ſeminary evacuation of both Sexes in conjunction: then <hi>curdled me like cheeſe;</hi> that is the changing of that to a groſſer matter, <hi>congealed blood:</hi> then <hi>clothed me with fleſh and skin:</hi> that is, the incarnation of that condenſed <hi>blood:</hi> then <hi>fenced me with bones and ſinnues;</hi> that is, that carnate matter was <hi>formed</hi> into humane ſhape, and grew into members: then <hi>grantedſt me life:</hi> that is, began to breath: whence obſerve, that in aſcribing the whole work to God, he doth aſcribe it to one kind only, and not partly mediate, partly imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate; for he aſcribeth even the evacuation of ſeed in carnall copulation, and the conception of fleſh and bones in as high a meaſure, (yea, to take away all cavil rather a greater,) as he doth his life; <hi>poured, clothed,</hi> and <hi>fenced</hi> imply a more abſolute act then <hi>granting,</hi> which is but a ſufferance, permiſſion, or aſſenting: therefore, his conception was meerly and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly naturall: according to that of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. <hi>Behold, I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my mother conceive me.</hi> And to this adde that of <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>The Lord formeth the ſpirit of man within him.</hi> Whence it is clear, that whole man <hi>fleſh and ſpirit</hi> is a ſecond act, formed in the wombe; otherwiſe fleſh as well as ſpirit muſt be created, which all deny.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>Adam begat a ſon in his own likeneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 15. 16. <hi>My ſubſtance was not hid from thee, when I was made in a ſecret place, and curiouſly wrought in the loweſt parts of the Earth: thine eyes did ſee my maſſe: yet being imperfect, and in thy book all my members were written, which in continuance were faſhioned, when as yet was none of them:</hi> whence is evident, that his whole Perſon was an act of nature in his mothers wombe or <hi>ſecret place;</hi> what of him was in the Book of Gods providence, he declareth, was <hi>made</hi> (not created) <hi>in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place,</hi> to wit, his ſubſtance or <hi>Maſſe,</hi> all that went to the ſubject <hi>man,</hi> and I hope the <hi>Soularies</hi> will not blot his Soul out of the Book of Gods providence, or ſay it was no part of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 31. <hi>Thou ſhalt conceive in thy wombe and bring forth a ſon:</hi> whence obſerve, that what ſhe was to bring forth, ſhe was to conceive, to wit a ſon; and none will deny, Chriſt was borne compleat man, in all things as we are, ſin excepted: And if any ſcruple ariſe from <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>He was made of the ſeed of David according to the fleſh,</hi> I Anſwer. That it is a diſtinction of his manhood from his godhead, as all Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters agree.</p>
               <p>Gen. 4. 1. <hi>She conceived and bare Cain:</hi> ſee the like <hi>cap.</hi> 38. 3. 4. 5. Judg. 13. 3. 5. 7. And Job 3. 3. <hi>There is a man child conceived.</hi> And Gen. 17. 6.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171460:24"/> 
                  <hi>And Kings ſhall come out of thee.</hi> ver. 17. <hi>twelve Princes ſhall he beget.</hi> And Judg. 8. 30. <hi>Gideon had</hi> 70. <hi>Sons out of his body begotten.</hi> And Num. 5. <hi>Then ſhe ſhall be free, and ſhall conceive ſeed.</hi> and Heb. 11. 11. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Gen. 17. 8. and ſuch like, plainly ſhew mans <hi>procreation</hi> wholy <hi>naturall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>That which is borne of the fleſh, is fleſh; and that which is borne of the ſpirit, is ſpirit:</hi> Here is the naturall birth by nature, and the ſpirituall birth by grace declared each in his kind, the one a meer naturall, the other a ſupernaturall work: It is therefore inavoydablely true, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Soul cannot be ſaved; for what is not borne again cannot be ſaved, as the immediate words teſtifie, <hi>except a man be borne again, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> So then, the ſoul as well as the body is <hi>born,</hi> that is, proceeds from the fleſh, except we be born without it: Wherefore, they are no more <hi>twaine, but one fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having found Mans Foundation to be wholy in the <hi>Duſt,</hi> from thence taken, and thither to returne: Let this then be the uſe of all: That man hath not wherewith at all to boaſt no more then of dirt under his feet, but is provoked wholy out of himſelf, to caſt himſelf wholy on <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> with whom in God <hi>our lives are hid,</hi> that when he <hi>who is our life</hi> ſhall appeare, he might alſo with him appeare in glory, to whom be the honour of our immortality for ever, and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
